All right.
好的。
All right, so some quick things, administrative things from from last class,
好的，上节课的一些快速的东西，行政的东西，
it's only been one day. We already got emails,
才过了一天，我们已经收到电子邮件了，
so the first thing is that,
第一件事是，
I made a mistake last class,
上节课我犯了一个错误，
I said Ted Codd got his PhD at Penn,
我说 Ted Codd 在宾夕法尼亚大学获得了博士学位，
he got his PhD at Michigan,
他实际是在密歇根获得博士学位，
where all the great data people got their PHDs,
所有优秀的数据人都在那里获得了博士学位，
so Michael Stonebraker got his PHD there,
Michael Stonebraker 在那里获得了他的博士学位，
Ted Codd got his PHD there,
Ted Codd 在那里得到了他的博士学位，
David DeWitt another famous Davis guy,
David Dewitt 也是，另一个著名的 David ，
so it was not Penn it was, it was Michigan.
所以不是宾夕法尼亚，而是密歇根。
The other thing is people complain that about the audio,
另一件事是人们对音频有这样的抱怨，
Dear Andy, the audio of your class sucks,
亲爱的 Andy ，你课上的音频很烂，
so I can't see you afford a sound engineer, do it right,
所以我看你请不起音响工程师，是这样吗，
Andy, I love the course, but I can't listen to it,
Andy ，我喜欢这门课，但我听不下去，
because the audio is messed up,
因为音频太混乱了，
what happened while you're doing this,
你这么做的时候发生了什么，
I lost a way to live.
我失去了活下去的方式。
So that that was my fault last time,
所以上次是我的错，
so we're double recording,
所以我们正在重复录制，
so hopefully we won't have any issues with posting it this time.
所以希望这次我们在发布它时不会有任何问题。
And then we actually got emails about you,
然后我们收到了关于你的电子邮件，
which is surprising, right,
这很令人惊讶，对吗，
I saw DJ 2PL last month performing at the [bridge 21 over show] in Pittsburgh,
我上个月在匹兹堡的 [21桥表演] 中看了 DJ 2PL 的表演，
is that true?
这是真的吗？
All right.
好的。
You're very lucky DJ like that, he is expensive,
你很幸运得到像他这样的 DJ ，他很贵，
[] have a lot of money,
[]有很多钱，
does not have a lot of money, okay.
[]没有很多钱，好的，
Yo, DJ 2PL is ridiculous, is he single,
哟，DJ 2PL 很搞笑，他是单身吗，
I'm asking for my friend,
我在为我的朋友问，
and then she's like Taylor Swift without any thumbs,
然后她就像没有拇指的 Taylor Swift ，
I dont know means,
我不知道是什么意思，
so are you single?
那么你是单身吗？
I'm not.
我不是。
All right, anyway. That's their problem.
好的，不管怎样，那是他们的问题。
So today's class we to talk about SQL,
所以今天的课，我们来讲讲 SQL ，
the last class we spent time talk on relational model,
上一节课我们花时间讨论了关系模型，
we talked about how,
我们讨论了，
in my opinion, that a superior data model for every possible database,
在我看来，它是对于每个可能的数据库的高级数据模型，
you can sort of think of,
你可以认为，
the relational data model can be used to represent
关系数据模型可以用来表示
pretty much all the different schemes, that that are out there.
几乎所有不同的模式。
And then we showed how relational algebra was the building block
然后，我们展示了关系代数如何构建块，
for how we would execute queries or define queries to operate over, on a relational database.
关于我们如何在关系数据库上执行查询或定义查询。
So today's class is really now to talk about SQL,
所以，今天的课程真正要讨论的是 SQL ，
which is a declarative or non-procedural language for interacting with a database system.
它是一种用于与数据库系统交互的声明性或非过程性语言。
And we'll see over time is that SQL has evolved,
我们将看到，随着时间的推移， SQL 已经发展，
where in the beginning, in the 1970s, when it was first defined,
在最初的时候，在 1970 年代，当它第一次被定义时，
it was very strict about what a relational database should look like,
它对关系数据库应该是什么样子有非常严格的要求，
but in the last 40 years,
但在过去的 40 年里，
it's expanded to support things that don't look relational, like json, for example.
它得到了扩展，以支持看起来不像是关系的东西，例如 json 。
So let's, let's start the beginning, talk about how SQL got started,
所以，让我们从头开始，谈谈 SQL 是如何开始的，
and then we'll talk about the more interesting things you can do in modern versions of it.
然后我们将讨论在它的现代版本中可以做的更有趣的事情。
So the the SQL goes back to the 1970s
所以 SQL 回到 1970 年代，
and again for Ted Codd, when he wrote that first paper,
Ted Codd ，当他写第一篇论文时，
he didn't define a programming language for operating relational databases,
他还没有定义用于操作关系数据库的编程语言，
it was all mathematical,
这一切都是数学上的，
people said like, oh, the, the, you know, the paper was so inscrutable,
人们说，哦，这篇论文是如此深不可测，
nobody can understand it,
没有人能理解它，
if you actually read it,
如果你真的读了，
it's actually pretty easily understandable,
它实际上是很容易理解的，
it's just people didn't like math back in the day, I guess.
我想，那时候人们只是不喜欢数学而已。
So then he,
然后他，
some people at IBM saws paper
一些 IBM 的人看着论文，
and try to start building, you know, experimental relational databases
试图开始建立实验性的关系数据库，
to see whether they can actually take his mathematical ideas and put it, put it into practice.
看看他们是否真的能把他的数学思想付诸实践。
And so the very first relational database language,
最早的关系数据库语言，
as far as I know was this thing called SQUARE,
据我所知是这个称为 SQUARE 的东西，
that IBM invented in 1971
IBM 在 1971 年发明的，
and this was for a earlier project,
这是为了一个更早的项目，
that IBM was developing for one of the first relational database systems,
IBM 为最早的关系数据库系统之一开发的，
probably the first one,
可能是第一个，
which sounds it sounds like a weird experimental rock band,
听起来像是一支奇怪的实验性摇滚乐队，
it's called the Peterlee Relational Test Vehicle,
它被称为 Peterlee Relational Test Vehicle ，
but that was the first thing they built as an early prototype
但这是他们建造的第一件作为早期原型的东西，
to show that you could take ted codd's ideas and actually put it into a real system.
表明你可以将 Ted Codd 的想法实际应用到真实系统中。
The problem with SQUARE, though, is that,
然而， SQUARE 的问题是，
you can never actually reuse it,
你永远不能真正重用它，
because you had to write in weird notation vertically,
因为你必须垂直编写奇怪的符号，
which you can't really do,
而你实际上不能这样做，
so this is from the one of the papers, right,
这是论文中的一篇，
you would write,
你需要写，
this is how to do a scan on on the sales table by department,
这就是如何按部门在 sales 表上进行扫描，
like you would write in this weird vertical way,
你会用这种奇怪的垂直方式编写，
with characters that you wouldn't have on a keyboard even today,
使用即使在今天你也不会在键盘上使用的字符，
so no one actually ever did this.
所以实际上从来没有人这样做过。
So then IBM threw that away
然后 IBM 抛弃了这个，
and they started building a new query language called SEQUEL,
他们开始构建一种新的查询语言，名为 SEQUEL ，
spelled S E Q U E L,
拼写为 S E Q U E L ，
for the System R project,
对于 System R 项目，
which is a system we'll talk about throughout the semester.
这是我们将在整个学期中讨论的。
But this was the the second relational database system that IBM started building
但这是 IBM 开始构建的第二个关系数据库系统，
to try to show that Ted Codd's work could actually be done.
试图证明 Ted Codd 的工作实际上是可以完成的。
The Peter Lee one that was in the UK,
Peter Lee 团队是在英国，
that was a small team,
那是一个很小的团队，
the System R project was in San Jose at IBM research
System R 项目在圣何塞的 IBM 研究中心，
and that that was a major, major undertaking.
这是一项非常重要的任务。
So they defined SQL back in 1972,
所以他们早在 1972 年就定义了 SQL ，
this was Don Chamberlin and Boyce,
这是 Don Chamberlin 和 Boyce ，
they work in this query language
他们使用这种查询语言，
and the idea is the Structured English Query Language,
他们的想法是结构化英语查询语言，
but in the 1980s,
但是在 1980 年代，
when, when IBM put out a commercial relational database system,
当 IBM 推出商业关系数据库系统时，
they got sued for the term SEQUEL, like the name SEQUEL,
他们被起诉使用术语 SEQUEL ，比如名字 SEQUEL ，
because there was some other system or some other piece of software that was using it,
因为有其他系统或其他软件在使用它，
so then they just reverted it back to SQL,
所以他们就将其[恢复]为 SQL ，
just the letters, the Structured Query Language.
只有字母，结构化查询语言。
There was another very famous project at the same time
同一时间还有另一个非常著名的项目，
at Berkeley in the 1970s,
在 1970 年代的伯克利，
when System R was getting started,
当 System R 刚刚开始时，
called Ingres,
这个项目叫做 Ingres ，
who here heard of Ingres?
这里有人听说过 Ingres 吗？
Nobody, who here hears of Postgres?
没人，有人听说过 Postgres ？
You want to know why postgres is called Postgres,
你想知道为什么 Postgres 被称为 Postgres ，
because it's Post-Ingres,
因为它是 Post-Ingres ，
the guy that built, Stonebraker, when he built Ingres,
Stonebraker 当他构建 Ingres 时，
he commercialized it in the the late 1970s
他在 1970 年代末将其商业化，
and then went back to Berkeley 1980s,
然后在 1980 年代回到伯克利，
they built a new system,
他们建立了一个新的系统，
that was supposed to be Post-Ingres,
这个系统应该是 Post-Ingres ，
that's why it's called Postgres.
这就是为什么它被称为 Postgres 。
The Postgres, sorry, Ingres had this other query language, called QUEL,
Postgres ，抱歉， Ingres 有另一种查询语言，称为 QUEL ，
and so SQL, the [plan] of the words is that, [] the SQL to QUEL,
所以 SQL 单词的[计划]是， SQL 到 QUEL ，
because they the IBM guys knew what what the Berkeley people were doing
因为 IBM 的人知道伯克利的人在做什么，
and they would try to build a better query language.
他们会试图构建一种更好的查询语言。
Stonebraker would argue that QUEL is better,
Stonebraker 会辩称 QUEL 更好，
but of course no one uses that today.
但当然今天没有人使用它。
IBM released a couple of,
IBM 发布了几款，
in the 1970s, IBM was making a lot of money off of IMS,
在 1970 年代， IBM 从 IMS 上赚了很多钱，
which is a non relational system, didn't support SQL,
这是一个非关系型系统，不支持 SQL ，
and then they realized that SQL was going to go somewhere,
然后他们意识到 SQL 会有用武之地，
relational database were going to go somewhere,
关系数据库也会有用武之地，
so they released a much early prototypes, like System/38 SQL/DS,
所以，他们发布了更早的原型，比如 System/38 SQL/DS ，
but the big one that that really took off was DB2,
但真正成功的是 DB2 ，
which is still around today.
它至今仍在使用。
Again, IBM was a big juggernaut in the computing world,
IBM 是计算机界的巨头，
so whatever IBM said they were going to do,
所以无论 IBM 说他们要做什么，
that sort of became the de facto standard,
这都成了事实上的标准，
so when IBM came out with a relational database that supported SQL,
所以，当 IBM 推出支持 SQL 的关系数据库时，
even though there were competing languages like QUEL,
尽管存在像 QUEL 这样的竞争语言，
everyone coalesced around around SQL.
但每个人都聚集在 SQL 周围。
So, SQL became a standard in, a ANSI standard,
所以， SQL 成为了 ANSI 标准，
it was American Standard Institute,
它是美国国家标准学会，
in 1986,
在 1986 年，
and it became an international standard in 1987.
并于 1987 年成为国际标准。
And so even though it's a 50 60 year old language now,
尽管它现在是一个有 50 60 年历史的语言，
it has evolved and expanded over time.
但它已经随着时间的推移而演变和扩展。
So the latest version of the SQL standard actually came out in March this year in 2023
最新版本的 SQL 标准是在今年 3 月于 2023 年发布的，
and sees her list here,
看看她的列表，
the history of all the updates,
所有更新的历史，
the various features they've added over time,
以及他们随着时间的推移添加的各种功能，
and the main takeaway from this, from this listing here is that,
从这份清单中得到的主要结论是，
as as programs evolved, applications evolved,
随着程序的发展，应用程序的发展，
or the trends in in development software development has evolved,
或者软件开发中的趋势的发展，
SQL has, has, has moved along with it
SQL 已经一直在跟随它，
and adopted the ideas and adopted new new capabilities.
采用了这些想法，并采用了新的功能。
So, in in 2023, the big two features that have come out is
所以，在 2023 年，已经推出的两大功能是
now you can do property graph queries directly in SQL.
现在你可以直接在 SQL 中进行属性图查询。
So somebody brought up Neo4j last class,
所以上节课有人提到了 Neo4j ，
that's, that's a special purpose graph data model database system,
那就是一个特殊用途的图形数据模型数据库系统，
but now you don't need that anymore,
但是现在你不再需要它了，
because now you can run graph queries directly in SQL,
因为你现在可以直接在 SQL 中运行图形查询，
because the SQL standard supports it.
因为 SQL 标准支持它。
They also add support for multi dimensional arrays,
它们还添加了对多维数组的支持，
so I said before,
我之前说过，
that a lot of machine learning stuff is based on arrays or matrices,
很多机器学习的东西都是基于数组或矩阵的，
now you can operate directly on SQL these things.
现在你可以直接在 SQL 上操作这些东西。
Now just because the standard has defines it,
现在，仅仅因为标准有定义，
doesn't mean every system is going to support it, right,
并不意味着每个系统都会支持它，
I don't think any system really supports the multi dimensional array stuff,
我不认为任何系统真正支持多维数组的东西，
Oracle supports the property graph stuff,
Oracle 支持属性图之类的东西，
Postgres will eventually get there,
Postgres 最终将到达那里，
DuckDB eventually, DuckDB has a prototype for it.
DuckDB 最终会到达， DuckdB 有一个原型。
But because it's in the standard,
但是因为它在标准中，
now everyone's going to actually be able to support it.
现在每个数据库都将去支持它。
So I would say, in my opinion,
所以，在我看来，
the minimum support you need for SQL to say that your database support SQL
要说你的数据库支持 SQL 的最小支持
is defined in the SQL-92 standard,
是在 SQL-92 标准中定义的，
that's like, SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE CREATE tables,
比如 SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE CREATE 表，
that's, that's the basic functionality.
这是基本的功能。
So again, even though sql is over 50 years old,
再说一次，尽管 SQL 已经有 50 多年的历史，
it's not a dead language
但它并不是一种过时的语言，
and there's updates all the time.
而且一直在更新。
And of course, every ten years, every five years,
当然，每隔十年，每隔五年，
some new technology comes out
就会有一些新技术问世，
and people say that SQL is dead
人们说 SQL 已经死了，
and it's about to be replaced,
它即将被取代，
10 years ago, it was NoSQL,
10 年前，它是 NoSQL ，
And the hot thing now is ChatGPT or vector databases,
现在最热门的是 ChatGPT 或矢量数据库，
so you see a lot of these kind of things on Twitter or on social media,
所以你在 Twitter 或社交媒体上看到很多这样的事情，
where they claim SQL is going to die,
他们声称 SQL 将会消亡，
because ChatGPT is going to replace it
因为 ChatGPT 将取代它，
or natural language is going to replace it, right,
或者自然语言将取代它，
this is all a bunch of hype,
这都是一堆炒作，
it's interesting, but it's not going to replace SQL,
这很有趣，但它不会替代 SQL ，
SQL was here before you were born,
在你出生之前， SQL 就在这里了，
SQL be here when you die.
当你死的时候， SQL 仍在这里。
And I've made public statements basically about this,
我已经就此发表了公开声明，
there's an article they quoted me in last year, some magazines or something,
他们去年在杂志上引用了我的一篇文章。
I basically said you need to know SQL,
我说，你需要指导 SQL ，
if you want to do anything in in computer science.
如果你想在计算机科学中做任何事情。
All right,
好的，
so the, in a relational language like SQL,
所以，在像 SQL 这样的关系语言中，
it's going to have three parts,
它将由三个部分组成，
there's going to be the DML, the data manipulation language,
将会有 DML ，数据操作语言，
that's how we're going to, that's our SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE queries,
这就是我们的 SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE 查询，
that interact with in our database,
在我们的数据库中与之交互，
would be the DDL, the data definition language,
将会有 DDL ，数据定义语言，
that's the CREATE TABLE statement, the CREATE VIEW statement,
即 CREATE TABLE 语句， CREATE VIEW 语句，
to create the entities of the objects in our database
用于创建我们数据库中的对象实体，
and then there be, we're not really going to cover this,
然后会有，我们不会真的讨论这一点，
but there'll be the DCL, the data control language,
但将会有 DCL ，数据控制语言，
that's for like security and access control,
用于类似安全和访问控制，
some systems allow you have,
有些系统允许你，
like, you know, you can specify what users are allowed to see
你可以指定允许哪些用户可以查看
what rows or what columns or what tables and so forth,
哪些行、哪些列或哪些表等，
so the SQL standard specifies for, for these things.
所以， SQL 标准为这些内容指定了（标准）。
Another big thing,
另一个重要的东西，
we'll see later in the semester is the definition of transactions,
我们将在本学期晚些时候看到的是事务的定义，
how do you define a bunch of SQL statements you want to happen atomically in an isolated way,
如何定义一组你希望以隔离方式原子发生的 SQL 语句，
and again, the SQL standard supports this.
同样， SQL 标准支持这一点。
So again, we'll see bits and pieces of this as we go throughout this semester,
我们会在这学期看到这些零星的东西，
but for today's lecture,
但在今天的课程中，
we're really going to focus on the first one, the DML.
我们真正要关注的是第一个， DML 。
And in reminder from, from picking up where we we talked about last class,
从我们上节课讲到的提醒一下，
SQL is going to be based on bags,
SQL 基于袋子的，
meaning there could be duplicates,
这意味着可能会有重复的，
whereas relational algebra was based on sets
而关系代数是基于集合的，
and we see some cases
我们看到了一些情况，
where we'll have to add extra stuff in our SQL statements to, to deal with that.
我们必须在 SQL 语句中添加额外的东西来处理这个问题。
So today, again, is supposed to be a crash course on modern SQL,
所以，今天应该是一个关于现代 SQL 的速成课程，
I'm assuming everyone, whether or not you know it or not,
我假设每个人，无论你是否知道，
you know enough from the SQL-92 standard,
你已经足够了解 SQL-92 标准，
SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE
SELECT INSERT UPDATE DELETE,
and I want to talk about the,
我想谈谈，
I want to talk about the more sophisticated things you can do with them,
我想谈谈你可以用它们做的更复杂的事情，
but, but the overarching theme also will be is that,
但是最重要的主题将是，
we will open up the terminal,
我们将会打开终端，
we'll try a bunch of these queries in different database systems,
我们将在不同的数据库系统中尝试一系列这样的查询，
and we will see that,
我们将看到，
even though there is a SQL standard,
即使有一个 SQL 标准，
there is an internationally recognized document,
也有一个国际公认的文档，
that says here's what sql should look like,
说明了 SQL 应该是什么样子的，
nobody implements it exactly that way, right,
没有人会完全以这种方式实现它，
everyone's going to have these weird nuances and quirks,
每个人都会有这些奇怪的细微差别和怪癖，
where they have different features or different nomenclature or syntax to do certain things,
他们有不同的功能或不同的命名或语法来做某些事情，
in some cases, different semantics of different operations,
在某些情况下，不同操作的不同语义，
where even though there's a SQL standard,
即使有一个 SQL 标准，
it's going to be different from one system to the next.
但每个系统都会有所不同。
Who did, take a guess who,
猜猜是谁，
who do I think is the biggest offender for the worst SQL implementationation,
我认为谁是最糟糕的 SQL 实现的最大罪魁祸首，
worse is not the right word,
更糟糕的不是正确的词，
but like the one that deviates from the standard the most,
而是像最偏离标准的那个，
let me take a guess.
让我猜猜。
The top four out of.
前四名是。
Yes, in the back, yes.
好的，后面的，好的。
MySQL, he got it right,
MySQL ，他是对的，
yes, MySQL is gonna be the of all these,
是的， MySQL 将会是所有这些中[]，
where they're gonna do all sorts of weird,
他们会做各种奇怪的事情，
more recently, they now have a flag,
最近，他们有了一个标志，
where you can make it be more strict
可以让它更严格，
and try to be more closer to the SQL standard,
并试图更接近 SQL 标准，
but for the longest time, they do a bunch of weird things.
但在很长一段时间里，他们做了一系列奇怪的事情。
And my problem is that,
我的问题是，
I first started using databases, relation databases in like,
我第一次开始使用关系数据库是在，
when I was in high school in the 90s
90 年代，我上高中的时候，
and we were using MySQL 3,
我们使用的是 MySQL 3 ，
so I have all these bad habits,
所以我有所有的坏习惯，
that like I picked up from MySQL
我从 MySQL 中学到的，
and I'm like oh yeah, this is what SQL is,
我想，哦，是的，这就是 SQL ，
then you realize,
然后你意识到，
when you start playing other systems,
当你开始使用其他系统时，
like this is crazy, they're doing some weird stuff,
这太疯狂了，他们在做一些奇怪的事情，
but it's gotten better,
但一切都变好了，
MySQL 8 has has certainly improved a lot.
MySQL 8 确实改进了很多。
All right, so we'll go through all of these aggregations, group bys,
好的，我们来看一下所有这些 Aggregations, Group by ，
the string date and time operations,
字符串、日期和时间操作，
that's going to be the one where we see all the problems
这将是我们看到所有问题的地方，
and then a bunch of other different ways to to interact with SQL queries.
然后是一系列其他与 SQL 查询交互的不同方式。
And another theme about what we'll talk about is
我们将要讨论的另一个主题是，
the goal of writing SQL statement oftentimes is to
编写 SQL 语句的目标常常是
try to do all the computation on the the database server itself,
尝试在数据库服务器本身上完成所有的计算，
within one sort of one overarching SQL query,
在一种主要的 SQL 查询中。
meaning we don't want to have to do a SELECT,
这意味着我们不必执行 SELECT 操作，
get some data back into a Python program or something,
将一些数据返回到一个 Python 程序或其他程序中，
then then then operate on it
然后对其进行操作，
and then push it back and do more queries,
然后将其推回并执行更多查询，
we want to try to do everything we can
我们希望尽可能做任何事，
on the on, on the server side, inside the database system,
在服务器端，在数据库系统之中，
because we want to be able to push the query to the data,
因为我们希望能够将查询推送到数据，
not pull the, the, the data to the query.
而不是拉取数据到查询。
Again, this make more sense as we go along.
随着我们的前进，这更有意义。
All right, so for today we're using a simple example database like this,
好的，今天我们将使用一个简单的示例数据库，
has three tables, student, enrolled and course, right,
有三张表， student enrolled 和 course ，
it's basically trying to mimic a university,
它基本上是在模仿一所大学，
there's students, they take classes and they're enrolled
有学生，他们参加课程，他们被录取，
and they get grades in the various courses that are there.
他们在那里的各种课程中获得分数。
Okay, so we'll use this as the sample database as we go along.
好的，我们将使用它作为示例数据库。
All right, first thing is aggregations,
好的，第一件事是聚合，
so aggregate functions are a, a way
聚合函数是一种方式，
to compute some mathematical computation on a a sequence of data or a bag of tuples
对一个数据序列或一个 tuple 袋子进行数学计算，
and you're basically going to going to coalesce it down into a single value.
你是要把它合并成一个单一值。
So the classic things would be AVG, MIN, AVG, MIN, MAX, SUM, COUNT,
所以经典的东西是 AVG MIN MAX SUM COUNT ，
you're trying to compute the min value of a column
你尝试计算一个列的最小值，
across all tuples, within within a relation.
在一个关系中所有 tuple 中。
So an simple example like this,
举个简单的例子，
say we want to get,
比如我们想要，
for the students, we want to count the number of students,
对于学生，我们要计算学生的数量，
so have a login, where the login ends with @cs,
如果 login 以 @cs 结尾，
do you have an @cs email address.
是否有 @cs 电子邮件地址。
And so we just put the count function here,
所以我们把 COUNT 函数放在这里，
and then inside of it, actually doesn't matter for COUNT,
然后放在它里面，实际上对 COUNT 没有影响，
but we're account that logins
但我们计算 logins ，
and then we have our where clause
然后我们有 where 子句，
specifying what tuple should qualify.
指定哪个 tuple 应该符合条件。
So again, in my example here, I'm putting login,
再说一次，在我的示例中，我放入了 login ，
you don't actually have to do that,
你实际上不必这样做，
you could put a star, that's equivalent,
你可以放入一个星号，那是等同的，
because again, it's just counting the number of entries.
因为，它只是计算条目的数量。
You can actually put 1,
你也可以放入 1 ，
again, also equivalent, it doesn't matter.
也是等同的，没有关系。
Inside, you can really put anything,
在里面，你可以放任何东西，
you can put 1+1+1.
你可以放入 1+1+1 。
And the database system should be smart enough to realize that,
数据库系统应该足够智能，能够意识到这一点，
in this last example here,
在这里的最后一个例子中，
I don't care what the expression is inside of the COUNT,
我不关心 COUNT 内部的表达式是什么，
and I won't actually do that math,
我也不会真正做那个数学运算，
because I just care about what's the count tuples that I have.
因为我只关心我得到的 tuple 的数。
You can have multiple aggregates in a single SELECT output,
你可以在一个 SELECT 输出中可以有多个聚合，
so here now we're going to compute the average gpa and the counting of the number of students,
所以现在我们要计算平均绩点和学生人数，
again, with that, have the @cs login.
同样，使用 @cs 匹配 login 。
And you get back a single entry or single record in the output result
然后，你将在输出结果中得到单个条目或单个记录，
for the two computations.
对于这两次计算。
Important thing to understand though, with aggregation,
对于聚合，需要理解的重要一点是，
since you're trying to coalesce down, you know, multiple tuples within, you know, to to a single scalar value,
虽然你尝试合并多个 tuple 到单个标量值，
you can't reference anything in the SELECT output,
但是你不能引用 SELECT 输出的任何内容，
that isn't, that isn't part of the aggregate.
那不是聚合的一部分。
So I can't do something like this,
所以我不能做这样的事，
I can't go SELECT the average gpa,
我不能 SELECT AVG(s.gpa) ，
after you join the student table, the enrolled table,
在你 JOIN student 表和 enrolled 表之后，
and then also spit out the the course id of the enrolled table, right,
然后还获取 enrolled 表的 cid ，
because this is not defined, this doesn't make any sense, right,
因为这没有定义，这没有任何意义，
there, there isn't,
这里没有，
you, you're taking multiple rows,
你使用多行，
you you're condensing it down, closing it down, collapsing down for the average,
你[压缩]它，以获得平均值，
what is the course id in this context, right,
在这个上下文中的 cid 是什么，
it's nothing.
它什么都不是。
So, if you, in this case here,
所以，在这个例子中，
you sort of look at this,
你看这个，
what you're really trying to do is,
你真正想做的是，
you're trying to get for each course id, get the average gpa,
你试图得到每个 cid ，得到 gpa 平均值，
so what you need to do is, what to call a GROUP BY clause,
所以，你需要做的是 GROUP BY 子句，
where you're going to project tuples into buckets,
你将 tuple 投影到桶中，
based on whatever the parameters are in the GROUP BY clause,
根据 GROUP BY 子句中的参数，
and then compute the aggregate on each individual bucket.
然后计算每个单独桶的聚合。
So you sort of think it like this,
所以你大概是这样想的，
if I first do the the JOIN between the enrolled table and the student table,
如果我首先在 enrolled 表和 student 表之间进行 JOIN ，
I have all the, I have all possible combinations based on the JOIN
我就有了基于 JOIN 的所有可能的组合，
and then now I'm going to split them up based on the the course id,
然后我将根据 cid 将它们分开，
because that's what I have in my, in my GROUP BY clause,
因为这就在我的 GROUP BY 子句中，
and then now I compute the average for the gpa, for each, for each of those buckets.
然后现在我对每个桶计算平均绩点。
Makes sense?
能理解吗？
And just matches up like this.
就像这样匹配。
So again, the main takeaway this again,
所以，这里的主要观点是，
you have to have anything that's in a,
你必须有任何东西在一个，
anything that's not part of an aggregation, has to appear in the GROUP BY clause.
不属于聚合的任何东西必须出现在 GROUP BY 子句中。
So again, in this case here,
再说一次，在这里，
I don't have the student name,
我没有 s.name ，
I I can't, I can't put that there,
我不能把它放在那里，
I'd have to put it in in the GROUP BY clause.
我必须把它放在 GROUP BY 子句中。
We can open the terminal if you want,
如果你希望，我们可以打开终端。
MySQL used to let you do this in some cases,
MySQL 允许你做一些例子，
but we can actually try and see what happens.
让我们试着看看会发生什么。
I hate typing on my, my Surface,
我讨厌在我的 Surface 上打字，
I'm going to use this laptop here,
我将使用这台笔记本电脑，
I'll log into it.
我会登录进去。
All right, so we want to do Postgres,
好的，我们要做的是 Postgres ，
I have a bunch of database systems running,
我有很多数据库系统在运行，
so the query we were trying to do was,
所以我们要做的查询是，
[essentially] this, right,
本质上是这样的，
select average gpa course id from enrolled joining enrolled table and student table, right.
SELECT AVG(s.gpa), e.cid FROM enrolled AS e JOIN student AS s ON e.sid = s.sid; 。
So Postgres doesn't let you do this,
所以 Postgres 不允许你这样做，
because it says the course id has to appear in the GROUP BY clause,
因为它规定 cid 必须出现在 GROUP BY 子句中，
that's good, that's what we expect.
这很好，这正是我们所期待的。
Let's go over to MySQL,
让我们来看看 MySQL ，
MySQL doesn't let you do it,
MySQL 不允许你这样做，
but let me see if I put it in the right mode by default,
但让我看看，在默认情况下是否将其设置为正确的模式，
right, doesn't let you do it,
是的，不允许你这样做，
but there's a way to,
但有一种方法可以，
it's enforcing, it's enforcing the what mode it's in,
它会强制执行某种模式，
if I go to traditional,
如果我转到传统模式，
then now run the same query,
然后，现在运行相同的查询，
it lets me do it,
它会让我这么做，
and it spits out course id 15-445,
它输出 cid 15-445 ，
is that correct?
这是正确的吗？
No, right, because what does that mean,
不对，是吧，因为那是什么意思，
it's the average gpa for all courses,
这是所有课程的平均绩点，
but that's spitting out one of them,
但是它却输出了其中的一个，
so that's bad.
所以这很糟糕。
So let's go now, take the same query
所以我们现在开始，使用同样的查询，
and we'll go over to, to SQLite.
我们将转到 SQLite 。
Who thinks it's going to work,
谁认为它会工作，
raise your hand if you say yes,
如果你回答是的，请举手，
and the work meaning it'll actually run the query,
而工作意味着它将运行查询，
I'm not saying the result correct,
我不是在说结果正确，
who thinks?
谁认为？
We have one yes, two yesesf.
我们有一个，两个是的。
Who says no?
谁认为不会？
Most people say no.
大多数人说不会。
It did it, right,
它完成了，
and it also spit out 15-445,
它还输出了 15-445 ，
is that the same value as my sql?
这和 MySQL 的值一样吗？
Yeah, gpa looks, sorry, gpa looks the same,
是的，绩点看起来，抱歉，绩点看起来是一样的。
All right, let's go to Oracle,
好的，我们转到 Oracle ，
Oracle doesn't like it.
Oracle 不喜欢这样。
Let's go to DuckDB,
我们转到 DuckDB ，
DuckDB didn't like it.
DuckDB 不喜欢这样。
So MySQL, you can do it,
所以 MySQL ，你可以这样做，
if if you, if you make it be,
你可以让它这样做，
more like MySQL 5.7 and 8,
比如在 MySQL 5.7 和 8 上，
but SQLite will do it.
但是 SQLite 会这样做。
So again, this is the first example,
所以，这是第一个例子，
we'll see it many times,
我们会看到很多次，
SQL standard says one thing,
SQL 标准说的一件事情，
but the different systems are doing different things.
但是不同的系统做不同的事情。
Next thing you do is have,
接下来你要做的是，
you can have a HAVING clause,
你可以有一个 HAVING 子句，
say, if you want to start filtering on on these aggregation, the aggregate columns you're generating,
比如，如果你想要在你生成的这些聚合列上过滤，
you can add a HAVING clause to specify
你可以添加一个 HAVING 子句来指定，
whether, how many, what people should match,
什么人应该匹配，
after you complete the aggregation, right,
在你完成聚合之后，
so say I want to get only,
比如，我只想要，
show me only the students that have an average gpa that's greater than 3.9,
展示那些平均绩点大于 3.9 的学生，
so in this case here,
所以在本例中，
I'm computing the aggregation SELECT average gpa as avg_gpa
我计算的是聚合 SELECT AVG(s.gpa) AS avg_gpa ，
and I'm trying to reference it here inside of my WHERE clause, right,
并且我试图在 WHERE 子句中引用它，
I can't do that,
我不能这样做，
because at this point, when the system is actually calculating the query,
因为此时系统正在计算查询，
it's computing aggregation as it goes along,
它一边运行，一边计算聚合，
it can't, doesn't know what the final result is,
它不知道最后的结果是什么，
so the easy fix of this is to have a HAVING clause,
所以，解决这一问题的简单方法是有一个 HAVING 子句，
which is basically telling the system,
这基本上是在告诉系统，
okay, formative aggregation is produce the output that's defined in the SELECT statement,
[形成聚合]是生成在 SELECT 语句中定义的输出，
and then apply this additional filter for HAVING.
然后应用这个 HAVING 额外的过滤器。
This is actually not correct either, In some cases,
在某些情况下，这其实也是不对的，
I don't think the SQL standard lets you do this either, right,
我也不认为 SQL 标准允许你这样做，
because even though I have an alias up here for average gpa,
因为即使我在这里有一个平均绩点的别名，
the data system can say, I don't know what this is,
数据系统会说，我不知道这是什么，
MySQL that you do it, Postgres does not,
MySQL 可以这样做， Postgres 不能，
so instead you have to basically write the the aggregation clause again,
除非你必须重新编写聚合子句，
and again, the database should be smart enough to recognize that,
同样，数据库应该足够智能，能够识别，
this average on the gpa is the same as that avg_gpa up there,
这个 gpa 上的平均值与上面的 avg_gpa 相同，
and therefore compute the same computation, don't perform, perform the same computation twice.
因此计算相同的计算，而不是执行两次相同的计算。
So essentially just doing this again,
所以，本质上只是再次执行此操作，
compute the aggregation and then do the additional filtering to throw out things you don't.
计算聚合，然后进行额外的过滤，以丢弃不需要的内容。
Makes sense?
能理解吗？
All right, strings and timestamps or dates
好的，字符串和时间戳或日期，
of when things get really get really weird,
在这里事情变得非常奇怪，
not weird, but like, really inconsistent.
不是奇怪，但是非常不一致。
So for string function, string operations or sorry, string data types,
对于字符串函数或字符串数据类型，
the SQL standard specifies that,
SQL 标准规定，
the, the case of the strings within the values,
值中字符串的大小写，
that I don't mean the strings and the select statements,
我指的不是字符串和 SELECT 语句，
I mean the actual data you're storing,
我指的是你存储的实际数据，
that they should be case sensitive
它们应该区分大小写，
and that when you want to have in your SQL statement constant strings,
当你希望在 SQL 语句中包含常量字符串时，
you want to use single quotes,
你应该使用单引号，
Postgres, SQL Server and Oracle follow the standard,
Postgres, SQL Server 和 Oracle 都遵循标准，
MySQL is, by default, case insensitive
而 MySQL 是，默认情况下，不区分大小写，
and then they both SQLite and and MySQL support
然后 SQLite 和 MySQL 都支持
both single and double quotation marks to represent constants and strings.
使用单引号和双引号来表示常量和字符串。
So let's do what MySQL does
所以让我们操作 MySQL ，
and see how weird this is.
看看这有多奇怪。
So let's go back here, right,
所以让我们回到这里，
so you can represent a constant like this, right,
所以你可以像这样表示一个常量，
so you can have a SELECT statement without a FROM clause in MySQL
你可以在 MySQL 中使用不带 FROM 子句的 SELECT 语句，
and I can represent,
我可以表示，
it basically takes whatever the input is
它基本上接受任何输入，
and I can, it'll spit it out,
我可以，它会把它输出出来，
so I put a comma,
所以我加了一个逗号，
like I can do like 1, 2, 3, like that,
比如，我可以做 1 2 3 ，像这样，
it'll make columns for all the things in the output.
它将对输出中的所有内容进行[排列]。
So for strings,
所以对于字符串，
I can have it as double quotes and single quotes
我可以放在单引号或双引号中，
in the case of Postgres, it won't let me do double quotes, right,
在 Postgres 中，它不允许我使用双引号，
can't do that,
无法执行这个操作，
because it's trying to look for a column name tupac,
因为它在尝试查找名为 tupac 的列，
that's the way you sort of escape column names,
这是你转义列名的方式，
but it'll, it'll support single quotes.
但它将支持单引号。
So in SQLite, they support both,
在 SQLite 中，它们两者都支持，
so that can go tupac like this,
可以像这样获取 tupac ，
and I can go with single quotes like that.
我也可以用这样的单引号。
In Oracle, it's single quotes,
在 Oracle 中，它是单引号，
but it isn't like queries without a FROM clause,
但它没有没有 FROM 子句的查询，
so in Oracle, they have this weird thing called the DUAL, the DUAL table,
在 Oracle 中，他们有一个奇怪的东西，叫做 DUAL 表，
and this is a fake table that comes with Oracle,
这是一个 Oracle 中假的表，
allow you to write these kind of queries against tables that don't actually exist, right,
允许你对实际不存在的表编写查询，
so then I can get that,
然后我可以得到，
if you try to do like, SELECT star from DUAL,
如果你尝试， SELECT * FROM DUAL ，
you just get like an X,
你只会得到一个 X ，
I think the newer version,
我认为更新的版本，
they got rid of the DUAL, you don't need anymore,
他们避免了 DUAL ，你不再需要，
this is, this is Oracle 21,
这是 Oracle 21 ，
so it's a rather newer version, right,
所以它是一个相当新的版本，
so like you can't do, you can't do this,
比如你不能这样做，
but like in Postgres or any other database system,
但在 Postgres 或任何其他数据库系统中，
you can treat SQL as like a calculator,
你可以将 SQL 当作计算器，
you can put whatever you want in clause like that.
你可以把任何你想要的东西放在子句中。
So, all right, let's go back to MySQL,
好的，让我们回到 MySQL ，
and let's look at some string functions.
让我们来看一些字符串函数。
So, I can call now,
所以，我现在可以调用，
I can do SELECT star FROM student WHERE name equals TuPaC,
我可以做 SELECT * FROM student WHERE name = 'TuPaC';
with weird casing
带有奇怪的大小写，
and then it matched on the string Tupac, right,
然后它与字符串 Tupac 匹配，
because internally MySQL is treating the varchars as case insensitive.
因为在内部 MySQL 将 varchar 视为不区分大小写。
So if you want to now,
所以如果你现在想要，
if you want to treat it like, you know, like any other database system,
如果你想像对待任何其他数据库系统一样对待它，
where it actually is actually looking at the case as a TuPaC,
它的大小写视为 TuPaC ，
you can add this BINARY flag in front of the, or keyword in front of the column name,
你可以在列名前面添加这个 BINARY 标志或关键字，
and that'll treat it as a binary string,
这将把它视为一个 BINARY 字符串，
like any other system,
就像任何其他系统一样，
in this case here, now it doesn't match,
在这种情况下，现在它不匹配，
but now it tells me I have a warning.
但现在它告诉我有一个警告。
So now I've got to go now call show warnings,
所以现在我要调用 show warnings ，
and this is MySQL specific,
这是 MySQL 特有的，
so now they tell me that,
所以现在他们告诉我，
the binary expression is deprecated and be removed,
BINARY 表达式已被弃用并被删除，
and they tell me at least how to write it correctly,
他们至少告诉我如何正确编写它，
so now I have to CAST the name AS a BINARY
所以现在我必须 CAST(name AS BINARY) ，
and then I can call it.
然后我就可以调用它了。
So if I change the casing again,
所以如果我再换一次大小写，
then I get Tupac.
我就会得到 Tupac 。
So this burns a lot of people,
这会让很多人感到痛苦，
because they up, you end up like thinking,
因为他们会想，
oh, if you don't know that your varchar is case insensitive,
哦，如果你不知道 varchar 不区分大小写，
you could store things multiple times,
你可以多次存储东西，
you know, thinking that it's going to be different,
以为情况会不同，
because the case is different,
因为大小写不同，
but MySQL says they're the same.
但是 MySQL 说它们是一样的。
Again, this is only MySQL,
再说一次，这只是 MySQL ，
I don't know any other data that actually does this,
我不知道有任何其他数据这样做，
so that's a weird one.
所以这是一个奇怪的特性。
The question is, why is the name capitalized?
问题是，为什么这个名字要大写？
So his question is,
所以他的问题是，
I'm telling you,
我告诉你，
so there's the data being stored with the case sensitivity,
数据是以区分大小写的方式存储的，
the comparison operator, when it actually executes the WHERE clause is ignoring case,
比较运算符，当它实际使用 WHERE 子句时忽略了大小写，
so it's not calling whatever string compare that you have in libc,
所以它不会调用 libc 中的字符串比较，
it's calling either their own version of it
它要么调用自己的版本，
or the case insensitive version of it,
或者大小写不敏感的版本，
because that was some decision that somebody made in the 1990s,
因为这是 1990 年代某人做出一些决定，
that has carried over today.
至今仍在延续。
Yes.
好的。
Why do they make that decision?
他们为什么要做出这样的决定？
Ask me that question at the very end,
最后再问我那个问题，
get through all the again,
从头到尾再说一遍，
it's probably because somebody just did it the one way,
这可能是因为有人只是以一种方式做了，
you know, decided how to do it,
决定了怎么做，
or MySQL, the guy was actually in many cases trying to follow what Oracle did in some cases,
或者 MySQL 在很多情况下试图效仿 Oracle 在某些情况下所做的事情，
but Oracle doesn't do this,
但是 Oracle 没有这么做，
I have no idea, right,
我没有头绪，
we can email the guy he still alive.
我们可以给他还活着的人发邮件。
So yeah, I think there's a lot of times where people just did stuff,
所以，是的，我认为很多时候，人们只是做一些事情，
because, like one person did it without really thinking through the, the implications of it,
因为，就像一个人做了事情，没有真正考虑它的含义，
or they're trying to copy some other system,
或者他们试图复制其他系统，
where they like out some other particular feature of functionality.
他们喜欢其他一些特定的功能。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
We'll see many examples are why would anyone ever do this, do it this way.
我们会看看很多例子，为什么有人会这样做。
All right, so I think I showed a query like this before,
好的，我想我之前展示了一个类似这样的查询，
just make sure you see it.
只是确保你看到它。
So there's this LIKE operation in in SQL
在 SQL 中有这样的 LIKE 操作，
and you use this for really primitive string matching or and pattern matching,
你可以使用它来进行基本字符串匹配或和模式匹配，
so you would use a, you call LIKE and then you would say,
所以你调用 LIKE ，然后你说，
you would have a percent sign to represent a wild card,
你可以有一个百分号来表示通配符，
so instead, if you're coming from the Unix world,
如果你来自 Unix 世界，
star regular expression usually means match anything or dot,
星号正则表达式通常意味着匹配任何内容，或者点号，
in SQL, it's the percent sign,
在 SQL 中，它是百分号，
and that'll match it any sub string, including empty strings,
可以匹配任何子字符串，包括空字符串，
but if you want to match one character, you would use the underscore,
但是如果你想匹配一个字符，你可以使用下划线，
and there is support for regular expressions,
而且还支持正则表达式，
I forget whether that is in the SQL standard,
我忘记了这是否在 SQL 标准中，
but everyone does it slightly different,
但每个人的做法略有不同，
you can write more complex string matching, string matching patterns.
你可以编写更复杂的字符串匹配模式。
There's a bunch of string functions that also come in the SQL standard
在 SQL 标准中也有许多字符串函数，
to do things you could expect,
可以做你所期望的事情，
if you're familiar with Python,
如果你熟悉 Python ，
there's all the python functions,
那么所有的 Python 函数，
upper case, lower case, sub strings, replacing strings,
大写字母，小写字母，子字符串，替换字符串，
all that, all that's in the SQL standard
所有这些都在 SQL 标准中，
and for the most part,
而且在很大程度上，
these are going to be pretty consistent across the the various systems.
这些都将在各种系统中保持一致。
Where things go wrong is,
不一样的地方是，
which we think would be the most simple operation, concatenating two strings,
我们认为最简单的操作，连接两个字符串，
that's where everyone likes to do something slightly different.
这是每个人喜欢做一些略有不同的事情的地方。
So the SQL standard says,
所以 SQL 标准说，
the the double bar is the way you can concat strings,
双竖线是连接字符串的方式，
in in SQL Server, they, they use the plus sign,
在 SQL Server 中，他们使用加号，
and then in MySQL, they don't have under the default mode,
在 MySQL 中，他们在默认模式下没有，
they don't have the double bar, they don't support the plus sign,
他们没有双竖线，他们不支持加号，
you have to use the CONCAT function, right,
你必须使用 CONCAT 函数，
and we can see that real quickly.
我们很快能看到这一点。
So, going back to MySQL,
所以，回到 MySQL ，
so, want to do something like this, right,
所以，想要做这样的事情，
I get another warning,
我又得到了一个警告，
I show warnings,
我显示警告，
and it tells me it doesn't like my syntax, right,
它告诉我它不喜欢我的语法，
that was the first one, sorry,
这是第一个，抱歉，
boom, I get two warnings,
我收到了两个警告，
says the double bar is synonym for the OR, and therefore it's to be deprecated,
说双竖线是 OR 的同义词，因此它将被弃用，
and they didn't like the way,
他们不喜欢我的方式，
I was sending along the @cs,
我发送的 @cs ，
so we now try to call,
所以我们现在尝试调用，
we change the sql_mode in MySQL,
我们修改 MySQL 的 sql_mode ，
to follow the sql standard,
为了遵循 SQL 标准，
now I can, I can get the concatenation that I want.
现在我可以得到我想要的连接。
So again, it's concatenation,
所以再说一次，它是连接，
it would be super, everyone should do the same thing,
它非常（多），每个系统都应该做同样的事情，
but again, in case of MySQL,
但又一次，在 MySQL 的情况下，
is some legacy thing from the 90s,
是 90 年代遗留下来的东西，
that they're trying to slowly undo.
他们试图慢慢撤销。
All right, date and time is probably the worst one.
好的，日期和时间可能是最糟糕的。
So the SQL standard defines a bunch of ways
SQL 标准定义了一系列方法，
to define date types, time types, also timestamps,
定义日期类型、时间类型以及时间戳，
different calendar types, Julian calendar, Gregorian calendar,
不同的日历类型，儒略历，格里高利历，
but how, again, how the syntax is going to vary, is going to be pretty annoying.
但是，再一次，语法如何变化，是相当恼人的。
So I want to give it now a demo,
所以我现在想给它一个 demo ，
where try to do what would seem like a simple calculation, a simple computation,
试着做一个看起来很简单的计算，
we just want to count the number days,
我们只想数一数天数，
since from today to the beginning of the year,
从今天起到年初，
it's like 230 something, 240 something,
好像是 230 天， 240 天，
just the number, the total number of calendar days.
只是天数，日历上的总天数。
So we're going to do this first in Postgres
我们将首先在 Postgres 中执行此操作，
and then we'll do this in, in MySQL
然后在 MySQL 中执行此操作，
and do this in, in SQL Server.
然后在 SQL Server 中执行此操作。
So the first thing we need to do is figure out
所以，我们需要做的第一件事是
how to get the current, date, the current time, right.
如何获得当前日期，当前时间。
Well, there's in Postgres, there's a function called NOW,
好的，在 Postgres 中有一个名为 NOW 的函数，
and that will give you, you get back a timestamp with the current date,
这会给你一个时间戳以及当前日期，
in, in MySQL, you can do the same thing,
在 MySQL 中，你可以做同样的事情，
in SQLite, they don't have a NOW function,
在 SQLite 中，他们没有 NOW 函数，
in DuckDB, DuckDB is going to follow pretty much Postgres for a lot of things,
在 DuckDB 中， DuckDB 在很多方面几乎都会遵循 Postgres ，
because it's they use the same same SQL grammar,
因为它们使用相同的 SQL 语法，
so they have a NOW function,
所以它们有 NOW 函数，
I go to Oracle,
我切换到 Oracle ，
Oracle does not have a NOW function.
Oracle 没有 NOW 函数。
All right, so there's another way you can get the timestamp,
好的，还有另一种方法可以得到时间戳，
so in the sql standard,
在 SQL 标准中，
there's something called, a function called CURRENT_TIMESTAMP, right,
有一个叫做 CURRENT_TIMESTAMP 的函数，
except it's not a function, it's a keyword,
只是它不是一个函数，它是个关键词，
and then in MySQL, they have the function, they have the keyword,
然后在 MySQL 中，它们有这个函数，它们有这个关键字，
in SQLite, they don't have the function, they have the keyword,
在 SQLite 中，他们没有这个函数，他们有这个关键词，
and on Oracle, doesn't,
在 Oracle 中，没有，
gives us a weird error about that one,
给了我们一个奇怪的错误，
we'll come back to that in a second
我们一会儿回来，
and they don't have the keyword,
他们没有关键词，
so they have the function, but we're getting this other weird error,
所以他们有这个函数，但我们得到了一个奇怪的错误，
datetime interval precision out of range.
日期时间，间隔精度超出范围，
Okay, so what's that,
好的，那是什么，
So now we got to go back, maybe,
所以现在我们可能得回去，
oh, because it's, it's, it's Oracle,
哦，因为它是 Oracle ，
It doesn't like having a SELECT clause without, a SELECT statement without a FROM clause,
它没有没有 FROM 子句的 SELECT 语句，
so let's add our fake table DUAL,
所以让我们添加我们的假表 DUAL ，
then, we get it right,
然后我们就正确了，
but it's the keyword, and not the timestamp, right.
但它是关键字，而不是时间戳。
All right, so now, so at least now we can get the current time of the current day,
好了，至少现在我们可以得到当天的当前时间了，
and so what we can do is now,
现在我们可以做的是，
there we can start casting strings or varchars into date types,
我们可以开始将字符串或变量转换为日期类型，
and then there's this EXTRACT function in the SQL standard,
然后在 SQL 标准中有这个 EXTRACT 函数，
that allows us to extract some part of of that data timestamp,
它允许我们提取数据时间戳的一部分，
so this is saying extract the day from
这就是，先提取日期，
and then today's date as a string casted into a date type.
然后将今天的日期作为字符串转换为日期类型。
All right, and again, there's syntactic sugar for all these different systems,
好的，再次，这些不同的系统有语法糖，
that that are like non standard.
它们是非标准的。
So in Postgres,
在 Postgres 中，
if I try to give the string, it's going to throw an error,
如果我试图给出字符串，它会抛出一个错误，
because it says it can't,
因为它说它不能，
I need to operate, the extract function need to operate on a date,
EXTRACT 函数需要要在日期上操作，
but you're giving me a varchar,
但你给了一个 varchar ，
but I can add these the two colons at the end
但我可以把这两个冒号加在最后，
and then put date at the end,
然后把 date 放在最后，
and then that's going to cast it to a DATE type.
然后，这将把它转换为日期类型。
Can you see that or no, sorry,
你能看到这吗，抱歉，
let me do this, yeah,
让我这么做，是的，
I know it's wrong, sorry, let's try it again.
我知道这是不对的，抱歉，让我们再试一次。
All right, so here, I can give it a string
好的，所以这里，我可以给它一个字符串，
and then I put ::date
然后我放上 ::date ，
and that converts it to a date,
这就把它转换成了日期，
but that's only in, in Postgres,
但这只是在 Postgres 中，
I can't do this in any other system, except for DuckDB,
我不能在任何其他系统中这样做，除了 DuckDB ，
because they follow the same standard, right.
因为它们遵循相同的标准。
So if I go to MySQL,
所以如果我去 MySQL ，
try to do the same thing,
尝试做同样的事情，
doesn't like that.
不像那样。
Go to SQLite, doesn't like that.
去 SQLite ，不像那样。
Go to DuckDB, Oracle is not going like that,
去 Oracle ，不像那样。
FROM DUAL,
FROM DUAL ，
doesn't know what a DATE is.
不知道 DATE 是什么。
And this DuckDB should do it,
这个 DuckDB 应该这样做，
because DuckDB follows the same grammar.
因为 DuckDB 遵循相同的语法。
So we can use EXTRACT function to maybe extract what the, the current date is,
所以我们可以使用 EXTRACT 函数来提取当前日期，
or try to figure out how many days since from now until beginning of the year.
或者试着计算出从现在到年初有多少天。
So let's start with postgres,
那么让我们从 Postgres 开始吧，
so it turns out, it's pretty simple with Postgres,
所以事实证明， Postgres 的情况很简单，
so we can just cast the string of today's current date to a DATE type
我们可以将今天的当前日期字符串转换为日期类型
and then subtract it from the string of the current, the beginning of the year
然后减去年初时的日期字符串，
and we could use, we wanted to, we could go back here
我们可以使用，我们想要，我们可以回到这里，
and use CURRENT_TIMESTAMP or maybe use the NOW function,
使用 CURRENT_TIMESTAMP 或使用 NOW 函数，
and this should work, right.
这应该会工作。
So that gets today, cast it as a date, subtracting,
所以获取今天，把它转换成日期，减去，
taking the today's date and subtracting by the beginning of the year.
获取今天的日期，然后减去年初的。
And we get 241, which I assume is correct.
我们得到 241 ，我认为这是正确的。
So let's try the same thing now in, in MySQL,
现在让我们来尝试同样的事情，在 MySQL 中，
so again, since they don't have the NOW function,
因为它们没有 NOW 函数，
we'll do it for casting,
所以我们将在转换时这样做，
so now we get a weird number, we get 729,
现在我们得到了一个奇怪的数字，我们得到了 729 ，
what's that,
那是什么，
and surprisingly, actually,
令人惊讶的是，
somebody on Youtube in a comment of [] places,
YouTube 上的一个人在[]地方的评论中，
told me what it was,
告诉了我这是什么，
and this is weird,
这很奇怪，
so the first number is today's current month subtracted by January,
所以第一个数字是今天的当月减去一月，
so 8 minus 1 is 7,
所以 8 减 1 等于 7 ，
then it's, today's what the 30th,
然后今天是 30 号，
so today's day subtracted by January first,
所以今天的日期减去 1 月 1 日，
so that's 29,
所以这是 29 ，
you get 729,
你得到 729 ，
that's wrong, I can't do that.
这是错误的，我不能这么做。
So what we can do instead is,
所以我们能做的是，
we can, we can, sorry,
我们可以，抱歉，抱歉，
we can get the,
我们可以，
there we,
我们到了，
so what we're doing here now is,
所以，我们现在要做的是，
we're getting the date of today and the beginning of the year,
获取今天的日期和年初，
converting it to a UNIX_TIMESTAMP,
将其转换为 UNIX_TIMESTAMP ，
UNIX_TIMESTAMP is the number of seconds since the UNIX epochs, like January first 1970,
UNIX_TIMESTAMP 是自 Unix epoch 1970 年 1 月 1 日以来的秒数，
so we're converting it now to the number of seconds from today since 1970
所以我们现在将其转换为从 1970 年到今天的秒数，
and then we subtract that from the number since January first
然后我们减去从 1 月 1 日以来的数字，
and we divide that by 60 seconds times 60 minutes times 24 hours,
再除以 60 秒乘以 60 分钟乘以 24 小时，
and we get 241.
我们得到二百四十一。
So this, this is my original idea
所以，这是我最初的想法，
and then turns out there's a DATEDIFF function in MySQL,
然后发现 MySQL 中有一个 DATEDIFF 函数，
you can do this,
你可以这么做，
but Postgres doesn't have it,
但是 Postgres 没有这个，
DuckDB doesn't have it,
DuckDB 没有这个，
see if Oracle has it, DUAL, right,
看看 Oracle 有没有这个， DUAL ，
they don't have it.
他们没有这个。
All right, so that's a MySQL, that's a MySQL thing.
好的，所以这是 MySQL 的东西。
All right, so now let's try in SQLite,
好的，现在让我们在 SQLite 中尝试，
so SQLite doesn't have DATEDIFF,
所以， SQLite 没有 DATEDIFF ，
we can't do that, that subtraction that we did in Postgres,
我们不能做在 Postgres 中的减法，
the best solution I could come up with is
我能想到的最好的解决方案是，
the convert the timestamp for today and begin a year to the Julian calendar,
将今天和年初的时间戳转换为儒略历，
which is the number of days since Julian Caesar's birthday,
这是自 Julian Caesar 生日以来的天数，
in whatever BC,
在公元前什么时候，
you laugh, but a lot of the banks ran off that in the in the up until the 80s, right,
你笑了，但直到上世纪 80 年代，很多银行都在用，
and then you get 241,
然后你得到 241 ，
but we're getting it as a, as a floating point number,
但我们得到的是一个浮点数，
so we can cast it as an integer and then we get 241.
所以我们可以将它转换为一个整数，然后我们得到 241 。
I, I forget how to do this in Oracle,
我忘了如何在 Oracle 中做到这一点，
I'm not going to do in Oracle.
我不在 Oracle 中做了。
The main point again is, seems like be a simple thing,
主要的观点是，这似乎是一件简单的事情，
but all these timestamp stuff is woefully different.
但所有这些时间戳的东西都有很大的不同。
Any questions about this so far?
到目前为止，对此有什么问题吗？
Why would you want a lower function?
为什么想要一个小写函数？
Good question.
好问题。
I mean, you might need it for data cleaning,
我的意思是，你可能需要它来清理数据，
you might want it for.
你可能需要它来做。
Yeah, it's a good question,
是的，这是个好问题，
maintain the standard, right,
保持标准，
it could be,
它可能会，
it doesn't have to be,
并不一定非得如此，
also in the WHERE clause,
也可以在 WHERE 子句中，
you can have it in the FROM clause.
你也可以在 FROM 子句中使用它。
So if I go back to MySQL, right,
所以如果我回到 MySQL ，
so SELECT * FROM students WHERE name equals Tupac, right,
SELECT * FROM students WHERE name = 'Tupac';
student, right,
student ，
so maybe I want to do this though, in my output,
所以，也许我想在输出中这么做，
get a lowercase like that.
得到一个这样的小写字母。
Yes, sorry, yes.
是的，抱歉，是的。
Yeah, so her question is,
是的，所以她的问题是，
why do people have all these weird idioms in, in their, their SQL,
为什么人们在他们的 SQL 中有所有这些奇怪的习语，
when at a high level, they seem to be all sort doing the same thing,
在高级别上，他们似乎都在做同样的事情，
but it's these one-off things are different
但这是[一次性的]事情不同，
and that's related to his question,
这与他的问题有关，
why, why are all these, why are all these different nuances for these different systems,
为什么这些不同的系统有这么多不同的细微差别，
because somebody was writing and thought it was cool, right,
因为有人在编写，觉得它很酷，
and then they showed their friends,
然后向他们的朋友们展示，
like yeah, that's cool,
是的，这很酷，
So the double colon and Postgres,
所以双冒号和 Postgres ，
I agree, that's cool,
我同意，这很酷，
that casting thing, but they only do it, right,
转换的事情，但他们只做这件事，
the DUAL table, I don't know what.
DUAL 表，我不知道是什么。
Yeah, so give another example,
是的，那么再举一个例子，
so there's a shortcut in SQL,
在 SQL 中有一条捷径，
to do basically SELECT *,
执行 SELECT * ，
so SELECT * FROM student, gives you all the tuples, right,
所以， SELECT * FROM student; 给你所有的 tuple ，
But in postgres, which I think is also in the SQL standard,
但是在 Postgres 中，我认为它也在 SQL 标准中，
I can just write TABLE and get that right,
我只需要写 TABLE 就可以了，
in MySQL, I can do that, that's cool,
在 MySQL 中，我可以这样做，这很酷，
SQLite,, doesn't like it,
在 SQLite 中，不是这样，
in DuckDB, they do it,
在 DuckDB 中，可以这样做，
but they also have another one,
但他们也有另一个，
I think you just go, I think you just go FETCH,
我想你只需要 FETCH ，
no, or is it FROM, right,
不是，或者是 FROM ，
you can just do that.
你可以这么做。
So they all had their weird idioms,
所以他们都有自己奇怪的习语，
I mean, so some of these things were, are, are based on customer feedback,
我的意思是，其中一些事情东西基于客户的反馈，
like the customer says, I want, you know, I need functions that operate on json,
比如客户说，我需要在 json 上操作的函数，
so somebody adds that,
所以有人加了这个，
and a lot of times these features get added before they show up in the standard, right,
而且很多时候，这些特性在它们出现在标准中之前就被添加了，
so the json xml is a good example of this,
json xml 就是一个很好的例子，
that got out of the SQL standard 2006,
这来自在 2006 年 SQL 标准，
but a lot of relational databases,
但有很多关系型数据库，
at the time in the early 2000s had some support for xml.
在 2000 年早期已经有了 xml 的支持。
And so what happens is,
所以发生的事情是，
like, the standards body is it's, it's a bunch of randos,
标准机构是一群陌生人，
it's the people at different companies,
它是不同公司的人，
so in the SQL standards body,
所以，在 SQL 标准机构中，
there's somebody from Oracle,
有来自 Oracle 的人，
there's somebody from Sybase,
有来自 Sybase 的人，
somebody from, you know, IBM,
有来自 IBM 的人，
and they show up the standards committee,
然后他们出现在标准委员会，
and they all try to get whatever they have, proprietary thing that they have,
他们都试图获得他们拥有的任何东西，
they try to get that into the standard, right,
他们试图将其纳入标准，
Oracle probably do this,
Oracle 可能会这么做，
the best example, more recently,
最好的例子是，最近的，
the Oracle got their version of property graph queries in the SQL standard,
Oracle 在 SQL 标准中得到了他们版本的属性图查询，
they base theirs on cipher, which is in Neo4j,
他们基于他们的密码，这是 Neo4j ，
that's now the PGQ stuff in a SQL standard,
现在是 SQL 标准中的 PGQ ，
so they got their extensions for graph queries in the SQL standard,
所以，他们的图形查询扩展获得了 SQL 标准，
because they were only ones ahead at the time.
因为他们当时是唯一领先的。
So that's how these things show up in the SQL standard,
这就是这些东西在 SQL 标准中的显示方式，
and so if everybody has competing ideas for how something should be done,
如果每个人都对如何做某事有相互竞争的想法，
you end up with the lowest common denominator or something could try to supports everyone,
你最终会得到最小的公分母，或者可以尝试支持每个人的东西，
but then no one exactly supports the, supports the standard.
但是，没有人确切地支持标准。
I'm not saying it's a good thing, but like,
我不是说这是一件好事，而是像，
it's we live in a different time also too,
我们也生活在一个不同的时代，
where there's so many different database companies
有这么多不同的数据库公司，
and there's one, there isn't one company, I say that owns the market
但没有一家公司，我说它拥有市场，
and and can bend people according to the will right.
可以根据意愿让人屈服。
So, I said before in the 1980s, IBM was, was the huge company, right,
所以，我之前说过，在 1980 年代之前， IBM 是大公司，
IBM was the the computing company,
IBM 是那个计算公司，
so whatever IBM said, that was considered the de facto standard,
所以无论 IBM 说什么，这都被认为是事实上的标准，
and so that sort of how we ended up with SQL today.
这就是我们今天使用 SQL 的原因。
But there isn't a company like that now,
但是现在没有一家公司像这样，
like the closest thing would be Google put out their standard of SQL called ZetaSQL,
最接近的事情是 Google 推出他们的 SQL 标准，名为 ZetaSQL ，
internally it's called something else,
它在内部被称为其他东西，
but they open source a parser and, and, and the and the grammar file and and the spec
但他们开放了一个解析器以及语法文件和规范，
for their version of SQL,
用于他们的 SQL 版本，
nobody uses it
没有人使用它，
and Google is huge, right,
而且谷歌很大，
the closest you're going to get today is Postgres,
你今天能得到的最接近的是 Postgres ，
a lot of these database companies,
很多这样的数据库公司，
when you start out,
当你开始时，
instead of building the grammar file from scratch,
不是从头开始构建语法文件，
you go take the Postgres one,
而是使用 Postgres 的，
hack it up and, and inject into your system,
将其修改并注入到系统中，
that's what we did,
我们就是这么做的，
and DuckDB took our code and they put it DuckDB,
而 DuckDB 拿走了我们的代码，他们把它放到 DuckDB 中，
like this bunch of systems are based on Postgres grammar,
这一堆系统是基于 Postgres 语法的，
because because this open source and they use it,
因为这个开放源码，他们使用它，
that's the closest you're going to get to a universal standard today.
这是你今天最接近通用标准的地方。
But again, I just showed you how there's FROM in DuckDB,
再说一次，我刚才向你们展示了 FROM 在 DuckDB 中，
but that's not in, in Postgres, right,
但那不在 Postgres 中，
they've adapted it.
他们对其进行了调整。
Yes.
是的。
His question is,
他的问题是，
what's the point of having a standard, if no one's going to follow it?
如果没有人遵循标准，那么有一个标准有什么意义？
I mean, there's a speed limit, everyone drives over it, right,
我是说，这里有限速，但是每个人开车都会超过它，
like,
就像，
I showed you much of SELECT statements, like the,
我向你展示了许多 SELECT 语句，比如，
and that were slightly different from one system to the next,
这在不同的系统之间略有不同，
but you understood what it was doing,
但你知道它在做什么，
basically the nuances of different systems,
不同系统的细微差别，
yeah, you may have to go read the documentation or ask ChatGPT what to do,
是的，你可能必须去阅读文档或询问 ChatGPT 要做什么，
but like at a high level, the the concepts are the same, right,
但就像在高级别上一样，这些概念是相同的，
just you know the specifics, Each system is going to be different.
只是你知道特性，每个系统都将是不同的。
Snowflake is a good outlier,
Snowflake 是一个很好的[异类]，
actually Snowflake started from scratch in 2013,
Snowflake 是在 2013 年从头开始的，
they didn't take Postgres,
他们没有选择 Postgres ，
they said they just came up with their own grammar their Snowflake grammar,
他们说，他们想出了自己的语法， Snowflake 语法，
that has things that other systems don't support.
有其他系统不支持的东西。
If I was, if I was building a new database system scratch today,
如果我今天从头开始构建一个新的数据库系统，
I would not do what Snowflake did,
我不会像 Snowflake 一样做，
it was a different time,
那是一个不同的时间，
I would start with Postgres,
我会从 Postgres 开始，
and then expand upon it the way DuckDB did.
然后像 DuckDB 那样对其进行扩展。
Okay, keep going, because still a lot to cover,
好的，继续前进，因为还有很多事情要做，
in the sake of time, I'm going to skip output redirection,
为了节省时间，我将跳过输出重定向，
because you're not really going to need that for the homework,
因为你在家庭作业中不会需要它，
let's jump ahead to window functions.
所以让我们跳到窗口函数。
All right, so before we showed aggregations,
好的，在我们展示聚合之前，
they were computing sort of one shot calculation across the entire input set
他们计算整个输入集的一次计算，
to the relation, that was being inputted to the to, to, for the aggregate function,
对于输入到聚合函数的关系，
that you're operating on the FROM clause,
那个你在操作的 FROM 子句（的函数），
but there's also times,
但也有一些时候，
where you may need to want to what is called a sliding calculation,
你可能需要进行所谓的滑动计算，
where think of like a rolling tally
想象一下滚动计票，
as you go from one tuple to the next,
当你从一个 tuple 到下一个，
as you're scanning along,
在你进行扫描时，
you want to update some, some kind of aggregate function,
你希望更新一些聚合函数，
so that for every single tuple, that you're output from your SELECT statement,
对于从 SELECT 语句输出的每个单独的 tuple ，
the aggregate is sort of snapshot in time of when that tuple was processed, right,
聚合是处理 tuple 时的某种快照，
the way, it's like an aggregate function,
它就像一个聚合函数，
where you're not grouping them into a single output, for every single final output,
你不会将它们分组到单个最终输出中，
for every tuple, it's going to have its own computation for that aggregation.
对于每个 tuple ，它对该聚合进行自己的计算。
And so the way this works,
所以，按照这种方式，
you would have like a, a function here,
你会在这里有一个函数，
this will be all your aggregate functions,
这将是你的所有聚合函数，
Min, Max, Count, Avg, as we saw before,
Min Max Count Avg ，正如我们之前看到的，
as well as some additional ones,
以及一些额外的函数，
and then you're going to specify what is the sort of scope or the range that you're going to compute this calculation for
然后你将指定要计算此计算的范围或范围的类型，
basically of how to slice up the data and source it and sort it.
基本上是如何分割数据并对它进行分类。
So let's look at some examples like this,
让我们来看一些这样的例子，
so I can have all the aggregation functions that I had before,
我可以拥有我以前拥有的所有聚合函数，
Min Max Count, so forth,
Min Max Count ，等等，
but I have these these additional ones,
但是我有这些额外的函数，
like the ROW_NUMBER, that tell me what row my tuple is, is in my output,
比如 ROW_NUMBER ，告诉我 tuple 在输出中的第几行，
as well as a rank, if I'm, I'm sorting them,
还有 RANK ，如果我对它们排序，
so if I have an ORDER BY clause, order students by gpa,
所以，如果我有一个 ORDER BY 子句，对学生按 gpa 排序，
I can tell you what your position is using the RANK function,
我可以使用 RANK 函数告诉你所在的位置，
you can't do that with a aggregation function,
你不能使用聚合函数来做到这一点，
because there's things that get collapsed down.
因为有些东西会崩溃。
So in this case here, this example here,
所以，在本例中，
I can do SELECT * ROW_NUMBER OVER and then the empty parentheses,
我可以做 SELECT *, ROW_NUMBER() OVER ，然后是空括号，
because I'm not partitioning it,
因为我没有对其进行分区，
and that'll give me output like this,
这会给我这样的输出，
what it'll tell me,
它会告诉我，
again, for all my output tuples,
对于我所有的 tuple ，
where do I appear in the list for that, right.
我在列表中的位置是什么，
If you have the OVER clause,
如果你有 OVER 子句，
you can specify how you want to group, group tables together or group tuples together,
你可以指定希望如何将 tuple 分组在一起，
when computing the window function,
在计算窗口函数时，
and then you can use the PARTITION BY, like GROUP BY, of how to how to group them up,
然后可以使用 PARTITION BY ，就像 GROUP BY ，来说明如何对它们进行分组，
so for this query here,
所以，对于这里的查询，
we're doing SELECT the course id and the student id from the enrolled table,
我们从 enrolled 表中 SELECT cid, sid ，
and I want to get the ROW_NUMBER of each, each student record in the enrolled table,
我想要得到每个学生记录在 enrolled 表中的 ROW_NUMBER ，
but then I want to partition it by course id,
然后我想把它按 cid 划分，
so I would get an output like this,
这样我会得到这样的输出，
for every single course, it would tell me,
对于每个课程，它会告诉我，
for every student id what, what position they are in that, in that group,
对于每个 sid ，他们在那个组中处于什么位置，
sort of [class] like this.
像这样的[课程]。
Then, if you have an ORDER BY clause,
然后，如果你有一个 ORDER BY 子句，
you can then control how the tuples will be sorted
那么你就可以控制 tuple 如何排序，
within, within either a partition or with, within the window, right,
在分区内或窗口内，
so in this case here,
所以在这种情况下，
now I can order the students by,
现在我对学生进行排序，
from the enrolled table, based on the course id.
在 enrolled 表上，通过 cid （进行排序）。
So there's a more complicated example here,
这里有一个更复杂的例子，
so we want to find the student with the second highest grade for each course.
我们想找出每门课成绩第二高的学生。
So for this one here,
对于这里的这个，
we're going to have a nested query, which we'll discuss in a second,
我们将有一个嵌套的查询，我们稍后会讨论它，
but basically I have a SELECT statement that has a FROM clause,
但基本上我有一个 SELECT 语句，它有一个 FROM 子句，
and inside that FROM clause, I have another query, right,
在那个 FROM 子句中，我还有另一个查询，
and I can, inside this inner query,
在这个内部查询中，
I can reference, here, I'm doing the lookup on the enrolled table
我在 enrolled 表上进行查找，
and then the outer query can just do filtering
然后外部查询可以进行过滤，
based on the output of this nested query,
根据这个嵌套查询的输出，
I'm going to cover nest queries in a second.
我会在稍后讲到嵌套查询。
So the first thing we're going to do is going to
所以我们要做的第一件事是，
group the tuples by the course id,
按照 cid 对这 tuple 进行分组，
and then sort them by the grade
然后按成绩排序，
and then we'll get the rank,
然后我们就会得到排名，
what is their position in the sort of list of grades, right,
他们在成绩列表中的位置是什么，
and then in my WHERE clause here,
然后在我的 WHERE 子句中，
I can reference now the, the window, the window function calculation of column, right.
我现在可以引用窗口函数对列的计算。
So any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
The question is,
问题是，
can I, can I make a window function using GROUP BYs,
我能用 GROUP BY 制作一个窗口函数吗，
let try it what you're saying.
让我们试一试你说的。
All right, so.
好的，那么。
All right, so, is in Postgres, right,
好的，在 Postgres 中，
so again, SELECT FROM the enrolled table,
同样， SELECT FROM enrolled 表，
and then we'll get the ROW_NUMBER where each student appears.
然后我们获得每个学生出现的 ROW_NUMBER 。
And then the second, excuse me, the second example was,
然后第二个例子是，
the course id, student id, and then the ROW_NUMBER,
cid sid ，然后是 ROW_NUMBER ，
we're going to partition it by the course id,
我们将按 cid 对其进行划分，
so then we're just going to order them and the output by the course id, right,
然后，我们将按 cid 对它们和输出进行排序，
so again, this case here, we see that we have,
所以，这个例子我们看到，
for each course, 15-445, 721 and 826,
对于每门课， 15-445, 721, 826 ，
here's the students that enroll in them,
这是注册的学生，
and then this is their position within, within each group.
然后这是他们在每一组中的位置。
And then my last example was like this,
然后我的最后一个例子是这样的，
and this is where you were asking, whether you can do a GROUP BY,
这就是你问的，是否可以使用一个 GROUP BY ，
we're now here again,
我们现在又来了，
so I can get the first,
这样我就能拿到第一个，
the inner query is going to get me the rank position of every record,
内部查询将为我获取每条记录的排名位置，
the rank where you are in the sorting output,
你在排序输出中所处的排名，
let me remove this part here first, right,
让我先删除这里的这一部分，
so here's, here's the output of the, of the, the inner query of the SELECT RANK,
下面是 SELECT RANK 的内部查询的输出，
so for every course,
所以对于每门课程，
I'm going to get the grades and I'm going to order them by the grades,
我都会拿到分数，我会按分数排序，
and then the rank is just where their position is
然后，排名就是他们所处的位置，
in the, you know, within the sort of list of the grades
在成绩列表中，
and the rank can have repeats,
rank 可以有重复的，
so if I say insert another record here,
如果我在这里插入另一条记录，
INSERT INTO enrolled VALUES,
INSERT INTO enrolled VALUES ，
so we need a student id, let's do, have tupac take,
所以我们需要一个 sid ，我们做 tupac 所使用的，
VALUES, course id would be 15-721
VALUES ， cid 是 15-721 ，
and let's say he got a, let's give a name, he's [].
他获得，给他一个 A ，他是[]。
What about I create,
我创建的在哪，
that order, by order by rank, maybe,
也许是按 rank 排序，
well, that that screws out the partition that, sorry, right.
好吧，那把分区破坏了，抱歉。
So, here what we're doing is,
所以，这里我们做的是，
every single course, again, we're getting the grade and sort of in the rank,
每一门课程，我们获得分数，然后按 rank 排序，
and so we inserted this record here, Tupac, we gave an A,
我们在这里插入了这条记录 Tupac ，给了他 A ，
but there was also another student who got an A in the same class
但是这里还有另一个学生在同一门课程中得到 A ，
and therefore they both have the same rank position of 1,
所以他们都有相同的排名位置 1 ，
and then for the student that got the C,
然后，对于拿到 C 的学生，
their rank position is 3,
他们的排名位置是 3 ，
so rank you can have duplicates. row numbers will not.
所以你可以有重复的排名，行号则不会。
So, yeah, so you're proposing to do what,
所以，是的，你打算做什么，
bunch of rank group,
rank 分组，
where,
哪里，
at the inner query, or what, sorry.
在内部查询，还是什么，抱歉。
The question is,
问题是，
is it possible to recreate the same query using GROUP BY,
是否可以使用 GROUP BY 重新创建相同的查询，
you wouldn't, you wouldn't be able to get the rank,
你不会得到 rank ，
because you wouldn't be able to get what what is my sort position,
因为你不能得到我的排序位置是什么，
there isn't a concept of that in, in SQL, right,
在 SQL 中没有这方面的概念，
so ROW_NUMBER is interesting, because it is,
所以 ROW_NUMBER 很有趣，因为它，
let's do that ROW_NUMBER,
让我们来做 ROW_NUMBER ，
make the point, switch a ROW_NUMBER,
换个地方，换成 ROW_NUMBER ，
ROW_NUMBER,
ROW_NUMBER ，
so ROW_NUMBER is interesting, because,
所以 ROW_NUMBER 很有趣，因为，
it's calling it rank, but trust me, it's row_number,
它叫做 rank ，但相信我，它是 row_number ，
it because, again it's bag algebra,
这是因为它是袋子代数，
there is no sort order in in these relations
在这些关系中没有排序顺序，
and that's a sort of weird concept,
这是一个奇怪的概念，
we think about programming like,
我们对编程的思考是，
what do you mean there,
你在那里是什么意思，
there's not ordering,
这里没有排序，
like because we're used to programming and under x86
因为我们习惯于在 x86 下编程，
where there ordering,
那里有排序，
how memory operations occur,
内存操作是如何发生的，
there isn't any of that here,
这里没有任何这些，
Everything can be unordered,
任何东西都可以是无序的，
so without a window function, you can't get a row_number,
所以如果没有窗口函数，你就不能得到 row_number ，
because there's no way to say,
因为没有办法说，
where do I exist in this position, in my position, my output,
我在我的输出中的这个位置，
Oracle does have row_number,
Oracle 确实有 row_number ，
they hide it from you,
他们对你隐藏了，
you can't get it, but like it's, that's just an Oracle thing.
你不能得到它，但它只是 Oracle 的事情。
So, so the window functions allow you to
所以，窗函数允许你，
condition doing the averages and all the other aggregates,
对平均值和所有其他聚合进行条件调整，
it allows you to get the order of things,
它允许你获得事物的顺序，
in a way that you would not be able to do it otherwise.
以一种你不能以其他方式做到的方式。
So I should showed nested queries before,
我应该在前面展示了嵌套查询，
but there just go through more, more detail.
但只是展示更多的细节。
So a nested query, nested queries, a really powerful concept,
所以嵌套查询是一个非常强大的概念，
sometimes called sub queries,
有时称为子查询，
where it allows you to have a query inside of a query
它允许你在查询内有一个查询，
inside, inside of a query,
在查询内，
you have multiple queries inside of overarching calling queries,
你可以在总体调用查询内有多个查询，
and you would need this,
你需要这个，
because you want to be able to express certain computations,
因为你想要表达某些计算，
it would be difficult to express certain computations without these nested queries,
如果没有这些嵌套查询，就很难表达某些计算，
without taking the data out, doing some computation
除非取出数据，进行一些计算，
and then putting it back in the database system,
然后将其放回数据库系统中，
so it allows us to put these things together
所以，它允许我们把这些东西放在一起，
to create more complex logic,
创造出更复杂的逻辑，
than we would not be able to otherwise do.
而不是其他方式。
And these inner queries can appear almost anywhere inside of a SELECT [],
这些内部查询几乎可以出现在 SELECT []中的任何地方，
but actually really any query,
实际上，可以出现在任何查询，
like you can have in the SELECT output, the FROM clause, the WHERE clause,
比如，你可以在 SELECT 输出， FROM 子句， WHERE 子句，
you can put an UPDATE queries and DELETE queries, right,
你可以放入 UPDATE 查询和 DELETE 查询，
and they can now reference all the tables within your own query,
现在，它们可以引用你自己的查询中的所有表，
it's a very powerful construct.
这是一个非常强大的[构造]。
So the basic idea is something like this,
所以基本的想法是这样的，
so here we're doing SELECT FROM the student table
这里，我们做 SELECT FROM student 表，
and then I want to get the name of a student,
然后我想要获取学生的姓名，
that is at least enrolled in one course.
他至少注册了一门课程。
So you can think of,
所以你可以想到，
this out, this SELECT [] in the top part,
这是上面部分的 SELECT ，
that's called the Outer Query,
称为外部查询，
and then this inner part here, we would call this Inner Query.
然后这个内部部分，我们称之为内部查询。
So, nested queries are notoriously difficult for database systems to optimize,
所以，众所周知，数据库系统很难优化嵌套查询，
because you think about the stupidest way to execute this query would be,
因为你认为执行此查询最愚蠢的方法是，
for every single tuple in my student table, rerun this thing,
对于我的 student 表中的每个 tuple ，重新运行这个东西，
get the list of all the student ids, then compute the IN,
获取所有 sid 的列表，然后计算 IN ，
the way to really execute this is,
真正执行此操作的方法是，
this is just a JOIN, for this one example here,
这只是 JOIN ，对于这里的例子，
this one's easy to do,
这个很容易做，
because, you know, you're looking for this, this thing to match something here,
因为，你在寻找这个东西来匹配这里的东西，
so you can do convert that to a [quality] predicate,
所以，你可以将其转换为[质量]谓词，
things get more complicated,
事情会变得更加复杂，
when there's non-trivial relations between the inner query and the outer query,
当内部查询和外部查询之间存在非平凡的关系时，
we won't, we'll, we'll come into that later in the semester,
我们会在本学期晚些时候讨论这个，
but, this is something, this is the hardest part of database systems
但是，这是数据库系统中最难的部分，
and the only system that does nested queries correctly is the system called Umbra,
唯一正确嵌套查询的系统是名为 Umbra 的系统，
which is a academic system out of Germany,
这是德国的一个学术系统，
DuckDB does it correctly now,
DuckDB 现在做得很正确，
for two reasons,
原因有两个，
one, because they copied what Umbra did,
一是因为他们复制了 Umbra 所做的，
it in papers, it's not like they stole the ideas,
它在论文上，并不是说他们偷走了创意，
and then we also sent them patches last semester out of 721,
然后我们上个学期 721 课程之后也给他们发了补丁，
so we fixed it for them,
所以我们为他们修复了它，
they can do some of these nested queries correctly with [],
他们可以正确地执行其中一些嵌套查询，
DuckDB is probably the best imitation of this,
DuckDB 可能是对这一点的最好模仿，
a lot of times there's a bunch of heuristics hacks,
很多时候，有一堆启发式的 hack ，
again, we'll cover this later.
同样，我们将在稍后讨论这个问题。
MySQL was always the worst,
MySQL 总是最差的，
it's gotten much better though.
不过，情况已经好多了。
So here's a query like this,
所以这里有一个类似这样的查询，
we want to get the name of the students enrolled in 15-445,
我们想要得到在 15-445 注册的学生的名字，
so we have the outer query,
所以我们有一个外部查询，
that we say we want to get the name from the student table
我们说我们想要从学生表中获得名字，
and then we want to have this WHERE clause,
然后我们想要这个 WHERE 子句，
we want to specify the logic,
我们想要指定一个逻辑，
that will get us the student id of the set of people that are taking 445,
它会让我们得到参加 445 课程的那组人的 sid ，
so this is a way to sort of think about,
所以这是一种思考方式，
how you want actually construct this,
你想要如何实际构建它，
start with the outer query
从外部查询开始，
of what the overarching computation of the output you want to be
你希望输出的总体计算是什么，
and then you figure out what the inner part needs to be separately.
然后得到内部部分单独需要的是什么。
So in this case here,
在本例中，
we can convert this English part here into a query like this,
我们可以将这里的英语部分转换为这样的查询，
but now we need to be able to reference it
但现在我们需要引用它，
or do the check that we want,
或执行我们想要的检查，
in the WHERE clause of the outer query
在外部查询的 WHERE 子句中，
and we use that IN clause that we had before.
并使用之前的 IN 子句。
So in this case here,
所以在这个例子中，
now we see that the student id in the,
现在我们看到这个 sid ，
in this WHERE clause, here are the outer query,
在外部查询中的 WHERE 子句中，
that's referencing the student id from the the outer query,
它引用外部查询中的 sid ，
but the second student id in the inner query,
但第二个在内部查询中的 sid ，
that's referencing the student id in the, in the, in the enrolled table.
引用 enrolled 表中的 sid 。
So the parser in the database system is smart enough
所以，数据库系统中的解析器足够智能，
to recognize the context of where a column is being referenced
能够识别列被引用的上下文，
to know which table you're looking at,
从而知道你正在查看的是哪个表，
in the cases where it doesn't know,
在它不知道的情况下，
that two things have the same name,
两个事物具有相同名称，
it'll throw an error
它将抛出一个错误，
and make you qualify the table name where a column is coming from.
并使你限定列所在的表名。
So there's a bunch different ways you can interact with nested queries,
所以，你可以通过多种不同的方式与嵌套查询进行交互，
you can set WHERE clauses,
你可以设置 WHERE 子句，
so you can have things like an ALL command or ALL operator,
你可以有 ALL 命令或 ALL 操作符，
that that every row in the nested query has to satisfy some kind of restraint,
嵌套查询中的每一行都必须满足某种约束，
you can have ANY,
你可以有 ANY ，
or sometimes called SOME is the alias, SOME,
或者有时称为 SOME ，它是别名， SOME ，
where you can say at least one row match my sub query,
你可以说至少有一行与我的子查询匹配，
the IN clause is that I showed before,
IN 子句是我之前展示过的，
it's the same thing as is equals ANY
它等同于 ANY ，
and then EXISTS,
然后是 EXISTS ，
just means that I want to find something,
意思是我想要找到，
where I know there's there's at least one match,
我知道至少有一个匹配的东西，
sorry, there's just one row being return,
抱歉，只有一行返回，
but I don't actually care what's in it.
但我并不关心里面有什么。
So I can rewrite the example I have before,
所以我可以重写我之前的例子，
instead of using IN, I can use ANY
不是使用 IN ，我可以使用 ANY ，
and it's considered equivalent.
它被认为是等价的。
And so we can show real quickly,
所以，我们可以很快地展示，
how postgres picks different plans for this,
Postgres 是如何为此选择不同的计划的，
and you see how it's actually being executed.
你可以看到实际它是如何执行的。
Right, so here's our query,
好的，这是我们的查询，
we have RZA and Tupac taking the class,
我们有 RZA 和 Tupac 选择了课程，
so in SQL,
所以在 SQL 中，
you can put this EXPLAIN keyword in front of it
你可以把这个 EXPLAIN 关键字放在它前面，
and of any query
放在任何查询前面，
and what that's going to do,
它会执行，
if the system supports it,
如果系统支持它，
it'll come back with the query plan
它会返回查询计划，
and tell you what operations would it execute,
告诉你它会执行什么操作，
if it actually tried to execute this thing, right.
如果它试图执行这个东西。
So when we run that,
所以当我们运行它时，
we get something like this,
我们会得到类似这样的东西，
that's going to tell us basically as a tree structure,
它会告诉我们基本上是一个树形结构，
so these are the leaf nodes
所以这些是叶节点，
and then it builds up this the final output,
然后它建立了这个最终输出，
so this is telling us,
所以这告诉我们，
Postgres wants to do aential scan the enrolled table
Postgres 想要对 enrolled 表进行强制扫描，
and then it's going to hash it,
然后它会对它进行散列，
because it's doing a hash one up there,
因为它在那里进行散列，
which we'll cover what hash is later on,
我们稍后会讨论什么是散列，
and then does scan on the student table
然后扫描 student 表，
and then now does by matching the student id,
然后通过匹配 sid ，
student id with enrolled student id.
sid 和 enrolled 的 sid 。
So Postgres was smart enough
所以 Postgres 足够聪明，
to convert this nested query into a JOIN,
转换这个嵌套查询到 JOIN ，
which is always going to be the fastest way to execute something,
这始终是执行某些操作的最快方式，
when you have these kind of references.
当你拥有这些类型的引用时。
We can try the same thing in MySQL,
我们可以在 MySQL 中尝试相同的操作，
but you get their explained output is terrible,
但你得到，他们解释的输出很糟糕，
there's a way to get,
有一种方法可以得到，
I forget the syntax,
我忘记了语法，
you gotta put like an EXTENDED or something like that,
你必须放入一个 EXTENDED 或类似的东西，
I forget how to do it in MySQL,
我忘记了如何在 MySQL 中这样做，
there's a way to get something a little bit better.
有一种方法可以让事情变得更好。
In SQLite, I don't think you can do this,
在 SQLite 中，我不认为你可以做到这个，
you can do this,
你可以做到，
what's that,
那是什么，
all right, SQLite,
好的， SQLite ，
they don't like the SELECT statement,
他们不喜欢 SELECT 语句，
which is surprising,
这是令人惊讶的，
why doesn't that work.
为什么这不管用。
See if DuckDB does it,
看看 DuckDB 是否能做到这个，
it give the output,
它给出输出，
DuckDB has very pretty,
DuckDB 有很漂亮的，
they give you, they give you nice little trees,
它们给你漂亮的树，
you guys are easily amused,
你们很容易被逗乐，
this impresses you, unicode output for,
这给你留下了深刻的印象， unicode 输出，
oh my gosh,
我的天，
but yeah, it gives, shows you what the physical plan is.
但是，是的，它你展示了什么是物理计划。
And then we can try it on Oracle,
然后，我们可以在 Oracle 上尝试，
right, has the right output,
好的，有正确的输出，
well, we need this another time,
好吧，我们其他时间再看这个，
there's getting the plan out of Oracle and SQL Server is a huge pain.
获得 Oracle 和 SQL Server 的计划是一个巨大的痛苦。
But I'm surprised that,
但我对此感到惊讶，
SQLite doesn't support this,
SQLLite 不支持这个，
I'm not going to debug this live,
我不会现场调试，
yeah, I don't know why it doesn't like that,
我不知道它为什么不喜欢那样，
let's try IN,
让我们试试 IN ，
ah, there we go,
啊，来了，
they didn't like ANY, like IN.
他们不喜欢 ANY ，喜欢 IN 。
Alright, so in SQLite,
好的，在 SQLite 中，
if I run EXPLAIN,
如果我运行 EXPLAIN ，
I get this,
我得到这个，
so the way SQLite does,
所以， SQLite 所做的方式，
which is, [genius], is that,
是这样的，
the way itutes your query plan,
它处理查询计划的方式是，
it converts the query plan into its own DSL op codes,
将查询计划转换为自己的 DSL 操作码，
and it has its own vm that runs the op codes,
它有自己的虚拟机来运行操作码，
like the JVM,
就像是 JVM ，
you take Java code, convert it into Java byte code,
你获取 Java 代码，将其转换为 Java 字节码，
and then the JVM executes it or interprets it,
然后 JVM 执行它或解释它，
that's what SQLite does.
这就是 SQLite 所做的。
All right, we'll discuss query compilations later in this semester.
好的，我们将在本学期晚些时候讨论查询编译。
So you got to put EXPLAIN PLAN,
所以你把 EXPLAIN PLAN,
PLAN, that EXTENDED,
PLAN ， EXTENDED ，
there's some syntax to get the real plan, whatever,
有一些语法可以获得真正的计划，
Trust me, it's there.
相信我，它就在那里。
All right,
好的，
so yeah, so they all do something slightly different
所以，是的，所以它们都做一些略有不同的事情，
and then if the system is smart,
然后如果系统是智能的，
you can try to convert it into a JOIN.
你可以尝试将其转换为 JOIN 。
So skip this and sake a time,
所以跳过这段时间，
because we got to get through,
因为我们要完成，
I want to get through LATERAL JOINs and and CTE.
我想完成 LATERAL JOIN 和 CTE 。
So LATERAL JOINs are a newer concept,
横向连接是一个较新的概念，
but, and not all systems are going to support it,
但是，并不是所有的系统都会支持它，
but the basic idea is that,
但基本的想法是，
it's going to allow you to have a,
它将允许你拥有一个，
a nested query reference data in in another query that is adjacent to it.
嵌套查询引用与其相邻的另一个查询中的数据。
So normally,
所以，通常情况下，
if you have two nested queries,
如果你有两个嵌套查询，
one nested query can't reference what's inside the other nested query,
一个嵌套查询不能引用另一个嵌套查询中的内容，
because it doesn't know about what's inside of it,
因为它不知道其中的内容，
but with a LATERAL JOIN,
但是具有横向连接，
it allows you to do this,
它允许你这样做，
you can almost think it's a for loop,
你可以认为这是一个 for 循环，
where one table, for every single, every single, every single tuple in the outer, outer for loop,
一张表，每一个外部 for 循环中的 tuple ，
you can do some, you can run some query,
你可以做一些查询，
do some computation here.
在这里做一些计算。
So in this simple example here,
所以在这个简单的例子中，
I have two, two nested queries,
我有两个嵌套查询，
I have a SELECT 1 AS x,
我有 SELECT 1 AS x ，
so this is turning back a single tuple that has one column with a value 1,
所以这返回一个 tuple ，它有一个值为 1 的列，
and then my LATERAL JOIN here,
然后我的横向连接，
can now reference the the output of this first query here
现在可以引用这个第一个查询的输出，
and just do plus 1 on it, right,
只需在它上加 1 ，
so I get I get 1 and 2 that way.
所以我使用这种方法得到了 1 和 2 。
Without LATERAL, you can't do this,
如果没有横向连接，你无法执行此操作，
because this would be treated as completely two separate queries,
因为这将被视为两个完全独立的查询，
which we can do this in Postgres and see real quickly.
我们可以在 Postgres 中执行此操作，并快速查看。
So, SELECT * FROM,
所以， SELECT * FROM ，
in an inner query, like 1 AS,
在一个内部查询中，比如 1 AS ，
sorry, yep, yep, yep,
抱歉，是的，是的，是的，
AS x,
AS x ，
AS t1.
AS t1 。
Right, so I can get back a single tuple, that has 1 in it, right,
好的，所以我可以得到一个 tuple ，里面有 1 ，
but if I try to put another nested query next to it,
但如果我尝试将另一个嵌套查询放在它旁边，
SELECT 2 AS y, AS t2, right,
SELECT 2 AS y ， AS t2 ，
I'm getting the cartesian product,
我得到了笛卡尔乘积，
but I can't reference inside of this thing,
但我不能引用这个内部的东西，
I can't go t1.x+1, right,
我不能做 t1.x+1 ，
because it doesn't know about t1,
因为它不知道 t1 ，
because those queries are running separately,
因为这些查询是分开运行的，
If I add the LATERAL keyword,
如果我加上 LATERAL 关键字，
now, my my second nested query can reference whatever is in the first one, right,
现在，我的第二个嵌套查询可以引用第一个查询中的任何内容，
and you can chain these things together as many times as you want.
你可以将这些东西链接在一起，想链接多少次就链接多少次。
Let's go back to it quickly
让我们快速返回它，
and see what the query plan for this one would be,
看看这个查询计划是什么，
in theory, you should convert this to a JOIN,
从理论上讲，你应该将其转换为 JOIN ，
oh, all right, it did a shortcut, ignore that,
哦，好吧，它走了一条捷径，忽略它，
because it basically says, I know what the answer is,
因为它基本上是在说，我知道答案是什么，
I don't have to run anything and just spits out the answer,
我不需要运行任何东西，只需输出答案即可，
that's what it did,
这就是它所做的，
like SELECT 1+1, it knows how to compute that without running a query.
比如 SELECT 1+1 ，它知道如何进行计算，在不运行查询的情况下。
Alright, let's have a more complicated example,
好的，让我们举一个更复杂的例子，
so say I want to calculate the number of students that enrolled in each course
假设我想要计算每门课程的注册人数，
and then I want to count the number of students enrolled in each course,
然后我想计算每门课程的注册人数，
and then I also want to get all the, the average GPA of all the students in that course.
然后我还想知道这门课上所有学生的平均绩点。
And so yes, you can write this without using doing a LATERAL JOIN,
是的，你可以不使用 LATERAL JOIN 来编写这个，
I just want to show you how to do this with a LATERAL JOIN.
我只是想向你展示如何使用 LATERAL JOIN 来实现。
So, there's two going to be two nested queries,
所以，将有两个嵌套查询，
where we had a SELECT statement on the the outer part,
我们在外部有一个 SELECT 语句，
and for every single tuple, that's in the course table,
对于 course 表中的每个 tuple ，
I want then compute the number enrolled students,
我要计算注册学生的数量，
and then again, for every single student in the course table,
然后，对于 course 表中的每个学生，
I want to compute the average GPA of all the enrolled students, right.
我想计算所有注册学生的平均绩点。
So I could write it as this,
所以，我可以这样写，
we have two and two nest queries,
我们有两个嵌套查询，
that are that are with the LATERAL keyword,
带有 LATERAL 关键字，
where again the first one here I compute the, the, the COUNT,
再次，这里的第一个查询，我计算 COUNT ，
again inside of it, I'm able to reference what's in the outer query here, the adjacent query,
在它的内部，我能够引用外部查询，相邻的查询，
and then for this one down here, same thing,
下面这个也是一样的，
I can have this one referenced there,
我可以使用这个引用那个，
now I'm not showing this example here,
现在我不在这里展示这个例子，
because you can try,
因为你可以尝试，
but, in the second LATERAL query,
但是，在第二个 LATERAL 查询中，
I can also reference was in the first one,
我也可以引用第一个，
these things get changed, to get changed together.
这些东西被改变，会一起改变。
And again, this is a different concept, when you think of SQL,
再说一次，当你考虑 SQL 时，这是一个不同的概念，
because SQL is unorder,
因为 SQL 是无序的，
we're not specifying the or we don't specify the order in which the database system should, should execute anything,
我们没有指定数据库系统应该执行任何操作的顺序，
we're not really doing that,
我们并没有这么做，
we're just telling it the [],
我们只是告诉它[]，
we we want the computation to to be performeded
我们想要的计算执行的顺序，
to compute the answer that we want.
来计算我们想要的答案。
So the database system can decide,
所以，数据库系统可以决定，
do I want to rewrite this as a bunch of JOINs
我是要将其重写为一组 JOIN ，
and just execute them all concurrently,
并同时执行它们，
or we can decide to do it one after another,
还是决定一个接一个地执行，
which we can then test Postgres real quickly
我们可以快速地测试 Postgres ，
and see what it does.
看看它是怎么做的。
I don't think I have copied here,
我不认为我在这里复制过，
yeah, sorry, I don't have to copy paste it real quickly,
是的，抱歉，我没有很快地复制粘贴它，
you can try it online later.
你可以稍后在[网上]试一下。
The last thing I want to show you is COMMON TABLE EXPRESSIONS,
我想向你展示的最后一件事是公用表表达式，
and so CTE were added 10 20 years ago,
所以， CTE 是在 10 20 年前添加的，
and this is similar to nested queries, or similar to,
这类似于嵌套查询，或者类似于，
if you're writing data to a temp table or something like that,
如果你要将数据写入临时表或类似的东西，
it's a way for us to specify a query,
这是我们指定查询的一种方式，
that we want to get materialized,
我们希望实现，
maybe we don't want to use that word,
也许我们不想用这个词，
we want to specify a query,
我们希望指定一个查询，
that could be stored in quotation marks at some virtual table,
该查询可以存储在某个虚拟表中，
and then we can have another query of reference whatever is inside of it.
然后我们可以有另一个查询，可以引用它里面的任何东西。
So in my really simple example here,
在我非常简单的例子中，
I have this WITH clause,
我有这个 WITH 子句，
I give my CTE a name,
我给我的 CTE 一个名字，
then I have my AS statement,
然后我有我的 AS 语句，
and then whatever's inside this parentheses,
然后这个圆括号里的任何东西，
whatever SELECT query here
这里的任何 SELECT 查询，
is going to get bound to this, this name here,
都将绑定到这个名字，
and then anything that comes below after the WITH statement,
然后在 WITH 语句后面的任何东西，
can then reference it as if it was a table, right.
然后可以引用它，就好像它是一个表。
So again, some like this,
再说一次，就像这样，
so I essentially the AS clause is binding things to names
所以， AS 子句绑定在名字上，
to whatever, whatever's inside my WITH statement here.
无论我的 WITH 语句里是什么。
So I have again a no table query,
所以，我又有一个无表查询，
SELECT 1 and 2,
SELECT 1, 2 ，
that's going to produce 1, 2,
将产生 1, 2 ，
has a one column of 1, one column of 2,
有一列 1 ，一列 2 ，
but then within my, within my WITH statement up here,
但是在我的 WITH 子句中，
I can give now names the columns,
我现在可以给列命名，
which then can be referenced down below in the query.
然后可以在下面的查询中引用。
You can do weird things too,
你也可以做一些奇怪的事情，
like you can actually, in Postgres will let you actually name the columns the same thing,
比如，在 Postgres 中，你可以给列命名相同的东西，
but then when you actually try to reference it below,
但是当你在下面尝试引用它时，
it'll throw an error.
它会抛出一个错误。
So again, this example where the syntax is, is roughly the same,
同样，这个示例中的语法大致相同，
but the semantics can be different across across different systems.
但语义在不同的系统中可能会有所不同。
Let's see,
让我们看看，
so let's see how we actually want to use this,
让我们来看看我们真正想要如何使用它，
so for this one, again,
再次，对于这个问题，
we want to find the student record that has the highest id that's enrolled in at least one course,
我们想找出注册了至少一门课程的最高 id 的学生记录，
again, you showed how examples how to do this with nested queries, that we do with JOINs,
同样，给你展示了如何使用嵌套查询，使用 JOIN 来实现，
but now we can do with the CTE,
但现在我们可以使用 CTE ，
where inside the CTE,
在 CTE 中，
first thing I'm going to do is,
我要做的第一件事是，
compute the MAX student id FROM the enrolled table,
从 enrolled 表中计算 MAX(sid) ，
and then now in my SELECT statement down below,
现在，在下面的 SELECT 语句中，
I can reference my CTE to get that maxId
我可以引用我的 CTE ，来获取 maxID ，
and then do my JOIN on that,
然后对其进行 JOIN ，
again, the database should be smart enough to realize that,
同样，数据库应该足够智能，能够意识到，
oh, I only have to run this, the CTE once, materialize it,
哦，我只需运行 CTE 一次，具体化它，
and then now I can reference it as if it was a temp table,
然后现在我就可以像临时表一样引用它，
in any query below that that calls it.
在后面的任何调用它的查询中。
And any question about CTEs?
还有任何关于 CTE 的问题吗？
Okay, there to finish up, right.
好的，就这样结束了。
So again, hopefully the main take away from all of this is that,
所以，希望从这一切中得到的主要结论是，
SQL is not a dead language,
SQL 不是一种已死的语言，
there's a lot of cool things you can do with it,
你可以用它做很多很酷的事情，
you want to try to do as much computations as you can within a single statement,
你希望尝试在一条语句中进行尽可能多的计算，
now it can be, can be nested queries,
现在它可以是嵌套的查询，
can do much of all the weird stuff inside of it,
可以做里面的许多奇怪的事情，
we wouldn't avoid the round trips going back and forth between the client and and the server,
我们无法避免在客户端和服务器之间来回往返，
because again, the database system should in theory be smart enough
因为从理论上讲，数据库系统应该足够智能，
to know what's the best way to execute the query that you're giving to giving to it,
知道执行你提供给它的查询的最佳方式是什么，
soon as you take stuff out of the database,
一旦你从数据库中取出一些东西，
do some Python code on it,
在上面做一些 Python 代码，
that's obviously outside the purview of the database system,
这显然超出了数据库系统的范围，
so we can't optimize it, can't optimize that, that Python code,
所以我们无法对其进行优化，优化那个 Python 代码，
if you keep everything inside of database system,
如果你把所有的东西都放在数据库系统里，
it should be able to make a good effort how to optimize it further.
它应该能够很好地努力如何进一步优化它。
And again, also the main takeaway from all of this is that,
再说一次，所有这一切的主要结论是，
there is a SQL standard, nobody follows exactly,
这里有一个 SQL 标准，但是没有人确切地遵循，
every single database system is going to be slightly different,
每个独立的数据库系统都略有不同，
people claim that, oh, it's great if you support SQL,
人们声称，哦，如果你支持 SQL 就太好了，
because then you can go and be portable,
因为这样你就是可移植的，
like if I write my application on on MySQL,
比如如果我在 MySQL 上编写我的应用程序，
I could very easily just port it to Postgres,
我可以很容易地将它移植到 Postgres ，
that is not the case,
并不是这样的，
oftentimes whatever database system you pick at the beginning,
很多时候，无论你一开始选择什么数据库系统，
that's what you're going to be stuck with for a long time,
你将在很长一段时间内被困住，
[].
[] 。
All right, so last thing,
好的，最后一件事，
homework #1, it be out today,
家庭作业一，它将在今天放出，
it's gonna be writing SQL queries,
它将编写 SQL 查询，
do basic data analysis,
进行基本数据分析，
this year we're gonna require you to do it on SQLite and DuckDB,
今年，我们将要求你在 SQLite 和 DuckDB 上做，
reason why is because,
原因是，
you write, you write the same query,
因为你编写相同的查询，
syntax will be slightly different, it won't be too bad,
语法会略有不同，不会太差，
but you'll run the same query and SQLite and you're run the DuckDB
但是你运行相同的查询在 SQLite ，在 DuckDB ，
and you'll see which faster,
你将看到哪个速度更快，
you have this epiphany, much faster than the other one,
你会有这个顿悟，一个比另一个快得多，
guess which is faster?
猜猜哪个更快？
More efficient.
更有效率。
He says more efficient queries, part reason, maybe.
他说查询更有效率，可能是部分原因。
That's not the answer either.
这也不是答案。
That's not the reason,
这不是原因，
okay, so you run these queries, DuckDB should be faster,
好的，所以你运行这些查询时， DuckDB 应该会更快，
you'll be like, okay why,
你会说，好吧，为什么，
that's the rest of this semester,
这就是这学期剩下的时间，
be it for SQL,
这节课是 SQL ，
next class we'll talking how you build a system.
下节课我们将谈论如何构建一个系统。